<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Akeeba Subscriptions User's Guide</title>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Nicholas</firstname><othername>K.</othername><surname>Dionysopoulos</surname></personname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>AkeebaBackup.com</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>April 2011</pubdate>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1.0.b1</revnumber>

        <date>April 2011</date>

        <author>
          <personname><firstname>Nicholas</firstname><othername>K.</othername><surname>Dionysopoulos</surname></personname>
        </author>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
      copy of the license can be found on-line at <link
      xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/fdl.html">http://www.gnu.org/licenses/fdl.html</link>.</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <abstract>
      <para>This book covers the use of the Akeeba Subscriptions component and
      its bundled modules and plugins for selling and managing subscriptions
      on your <trademark>Joomla!</trademark>-powered web sites.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>

  <chapter xml:id="intro-and-installation">
    <title>Introduction and installation</title>

    <section xml:id="introduction">
      <title>Introducing Akeeba Subscriptions</title>

      <bridgehead>At a glance</bridgehead>

      <para>Akeeba Subscriptions is a subscriptions management component for
      <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> 1.5/1.6 and compatible distributions,
      such as Nooku Server and Molajo. It is built using the Nooku Framework
      and the best practices for rapid web application development which
      ensure stability and security. It is licensed under the <link
      xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html">GNU General Public
      License (GPL) version 3</link> or –at your option– any later version
      published by the Free Software Foundation. It licensing scheme means
      that you are free (and, in fact, more than welcome) to install it on as
      many sites as you want, whenever you want and use it for as long as you
      want, no strings attached. There are no secret per-domain licensing fees
      and you can use it to sell one or several millions of subscriptions
      without any hidden costs. We love Freedom of choice as much as you
      do!</para>

      <bridgehead>The killer features</bridgehead>

      <para>Its feature list is nothing sort of amazing, either. Out of the
      box, Akeeba Subscriptions supports these features:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Streamlined administrator interface which can even present you
          an interactive sales graph and sales report as soon as you launch
          the component</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Rich subscription levels (subscription packages) editor which
          allows you to choose different images for each of your subscriptions
          and even a different order confirmation and order cancellation text
          to show to your users.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The easiest subscription management interface you've seen on a
          component. It will even show you your users' faces, powered by
          Gravatar.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Users can upgrade or expand (renew) their subscriptions.
          Renewing a subscription will create a new subscription which becomes
          valid the very second their old one expires. Users do not lose any
          of their subscription time when renewing, unlike most other
          subscription systems out there.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Full support for delayed payments, e.g. when using e-checks
          with PayPal.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Discount coupon codes which allow you to set an absolute money
          value or percentage discount for all or a specific subscription
          level and user, have publish up/publish down dates or a usage limit
          (e.g. the coupon code is valid only for the first 100 people to use
          it) – or a combination of any and all of the above!</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Automatic discounts for upgrading or renewing subscriptions
          based on the subscription level and days of presence in the
          subscription package. This allows you to easily create rules like:
          30% discount if you renew up to 30 days before the end of your
          subscription, 15% discount if you renew within the last 30 days, no
          discount otherwise.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Full support for complex tax calculations based on country,
          state and ZIP code. It fully integrates with the European Union's
          VIES system so that you can charge no VAT tax for intra-EU B2B
          transactions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The subscription form can work with or without Javascript.
          With Javascript it becomes a fully fledged, auto-validating
          subscription form. Without Javascript it works as a standard web
          form, accessible to users who do not wish / can not use Javascript
          on their browser.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Integration with Joomla! 1.6 user group mapping (Core and
          Professional editions): add/remove a user to/from Joomla! 1.6 user
          groups, based on his subscriptions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Integration with JUGA (Core and Professional editions).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Integration with third party components (Professional
          edition): K2, DOCman, JCE, NinjaBoard, VirtueMart, Tienda. More to
          follow in the near future!</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Content restriction: a content plugin to show parts of your
          content only to registered subscribers, without the need of any
          external tool.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Payment methods: PayPal (for personal, verified and business
          accounts) is supported out of the box</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Send emails to subscribers upon subscription, when their
          subscription/payment status changes and when their subscription is
          about to expire</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>All the attention to details that makes a component worthy of
          carrying the Akeeba label!</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <bridgehead>Support policy</bridgehead>

      <para>Please note that the software is provided free of charge, but
      support is not. You need to have an AKEEBASUBS subscription on
      AkeebaBackup.com to seek support regarding setting up, using and
      customizing Akeeba Subscriptions. If you have found a bug and wish to
      report it, however, you can do so even without an active
      AkeebaBackup.com subscription.</para>

      <para>If you are an existing AkeebaBackup.com subscriber you can get an
      AKEEBASUBS subscription at 50% off while we're still in beta!</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="requirements">
      <title>Requirements and compatibility</title>

      <para>Akeeba Subscriptions requires the following server-side
      configuration:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>PHP 5.2.6 or later. Running it on earlier versions will either
          be problematic or it won't work at all.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>MySQL 5.0.41 or later. Earlier database server versions will
          not be supported. Do note that earlier releases of MySQL are
          obsolete and not supported any more by Oracle (the company who
          controls the development of MySQL).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Your server must support the mysqli driver and your site must
          use it. If not, Akeeba Subscriptions will try to switch your site to
          mysqli upon installation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you are using the Suhosin patch for PHP, please <link
          xlink:href="http://nooku.assembla.com/wiki/show/nooku-framework/Known_Issues">read
          this tutorial</link> to avoid any potential conflicts. Support will
          not be provided if you are affected by this Suhosin issue.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Joomla! 1.5.14 or later (fully supported) or Joomla! 1.6.0 or
          later (partial support for now). We know that some things in the
          back-end do not work properly (they look ugly or have other visual
          artifacts) with Joomla! 1.6. Fixing them would break Joomla! 1.5
          compatibility, so please don't report them as bugs – we are just not
          going to fix them yet.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <guilabel>System - mooTools Upgrade</guilabel> system
          plugin MUST be enabled on Joomla! 1.5 sites.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Akeeba Subscriptions is compatible with other Nooku-based software
      which is using at least Nooku Framework 0.7 Alpha 2, such as Ninjaboard
      1.0.7 and later. It will not work properly together with components
      using earlier versions of the framework, such as Joomlashack's
      LifeStream. If you're in doubt, please try installing Akeeba
      Subscriptions on a copy of your site and test its behaviour.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="installation-instructions">
      <title>Installation</title>

      <section xml:id="installation">
        <title>Installation</title>

        <para>There are two available installation packages. The one with
        -noframework in its name contains only the component, modules and
        plugins of Akeeba Subscriptions. The one with -nooku contains
        everything plus a copy of the Nooku Framework. If you don't have any
        other Nooku-based software on your site, please install the regular
        package. If you have another Nooku-based software on your site, such
        as Ninjaboard 1.0.7 or later, please try installing the -noframework
        package first and, if that doesn't work properly, take a backup of
        your site and try installing the regular package.</para>

        <para>Installing the package is the same as with any other Joomla!
        component. Go to your site's back-end, Extensions, Install/Uninstall
        (Joomla! 1.5) or Extensions, Manage (Joomla! 1.6) and click on Browse.
        Locate the ZIP package and click on Upload and Install. If the
        installation fails, please refer to the installation troubleshooting
        section of this guide.</para>

        <important>
          <para>On Joomla! 1.5 sites you MUST publish the <guilabel>System -
          mooTools Upgrade</guilabel> system plugin for Akeeba Subscriptions
          to work properly. If you don't, the interface will appear broken and
          you will not be able to use the component. If you file a support
          request regarding that, we'll just reply with
          "<acronym>RTFM</acronym>" (RTFM is the acronym for Read The Fine
          Manual).</para>
        </important>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="installation-troubleshooting">
        <title>Installation troubleshooting</title>

        <bridgehead>Joomla! 1.6 is logging you out during
        installation</bridgehead>

        <para>The first thing you might observe is that <emphasis
        role="bold">Joomla! 1.6 is logging you out when trying to
        install</emphasis> Akeeba Subscriptions. This is due to a bug in
        Joomla! 1.6. Please <link
        xlink:href="http://docs.joomla.org/Why_does_the_administrator_logoff_all_of_the_sudden">follow
        these instructions</link> to fix the database table that causes this
        issue. After doing that you will have to log in again to your site.
        You will see that everything is missing from the back-end interface.
        Don't panic! That's part of the Joomla! bug. Just log out using the
        link on the top-right of your page, then log back in. Everything is
        back to normal and you can retry the installation.</para>

        <bridgehead>Joomla! 1.6 says "can't build admin menu" and
        fails</bridgehead>

        <para>On some other occasions, especially when trying to install or
        update the component after an installation error, Joomla! will
        complain that it <emphasis role="bold">can not build admin
        menus</emphasis>. This is due to another Joomla! 1.6 bug <link
        xlink:href="http://joomlacode.org/gf/project/joomla/tracker/?action=TrackerItemEdit&amp;tracker_item_id=25663">we
        have sent a patch for</link> to the Joomla! development team.
        Meanwhile, you will have to run a few SQL statements against your
        database with a database editor such as phpMyAdmin:</para>

        <programlisting>DELETE FROM jos_assets WHERE `name` = 'com_akeebasubs';
DELETE FROM jos_menu WHERE `menutype` = 'main' AND `alias` = 'com_akeebasubs';
DELETE FROM jos_extensions WHERE `type` = 'component' AND `element` = 'com_akeebasubs';</programlisting>

        <para>Remember to change <replaceable>jos_</replaceable> with your
        database tables' name prefix if you changed it during installation!
        It's easy to find out what it is. Take a look at the database and
        you'll see that all of your tables begin with the same few letters.
        That's your prefix. After running those SQL statements you can proceed
        with the reinstallation of the component.</para>

        <bridgehead>Version check</bridgehead>

        <para>Check your Joomla! version. Joomla! 1.5.0 through 1.5.10 can not
        install Akeeba Subscriptions. This is a limitation of these extremely
        outdated releases. If you have such a site, upgrade it. Joomla! 1.5.11
        through 1.5.14 may or may not be able to install Akeeba Subscriptions.
        Again, these are limitations of those outdated Joomla! releases on
        certain hosts. The only workaround is to upgrade your Joomla!
        installation.</para>

        <para>If you have Joomla! 1.6 make sure that you are using Joomla!
        1.6.0 (the "stable" release, not the RC or any of the betas). Mind
        you, we have only tested the installation with Joomla! 1.6.2 and later
        releases.</para>

        <bridgehead>Checking your temporary directory</bridgehead>

        <para>First, we will have to make sure that you are using a valid
        temporary directory. Many sites are configured to use the system-wide
        (/tmp) directory or an invalid directory, causing installation
        problems. In order to change your site's temporary directory setting
        you have to follow this procedure, depending on your Joomla!
        version.</para>

        <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Joomla! 1.5</bridgehead>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Go to your site's administrator back-end and click
            <guimenu>Help</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>System Info</guimenuitem>
            from the top menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <guilabel>Directory permissions</guilabel>
            link</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Scroll down the page and find the first <guilabel>Cache
            Directory</guilabel> line. It is the fourth from the bottom of the
            page.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Next to the <guilabel>Cache directory</guilabel> label you
            can see a path, e.g.
            <filename>/home/myuser/public_html/cache</filename></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Replace the <filename>cache</filename> word with
            <filename>tmp</filename> in that path, i.e.
            <filename>/home/myuser/public_html/tmp</filename> and note down
            this path. This is your new temp path.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Go to <guimenu>Site</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Global
            Configuration</guimenuitem> menu item from the top menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <guilabel>Server</guilabel> link</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Find the "Path to Temp-folder" and replace its contents with
            the new temp path from step #5.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Save your Global Configuration</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Joomla! 1.6</bridgehead>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Create a file named mynewtmp.php with the following
            contents:</para>

            <programlisting>&lt;?php echo dirname(__FILE__).'/tmp';</programlisting>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Upload the file to your site and access it as
            http://www.example.com/mynewtmp.php where www.example.com is the
            domain name to your site.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Write down what you see on the screen. That's your new
            temporary directory path.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Remove the mynewtmp.php file from your site.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Go to your site's administrator back-end and click on
            <guimenu>Site</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Global
            Configuration</guimenuitem> menu item from the top menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <guilabel>Server</guilabel> link</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Find the "Path to Temp-folder" and replace its contents with
            the new temp path from step #3.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Save your Global Configuration</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <bridgehead>Enable FTP</bridgehead>

        <para>On most shared hosts which do not run suPHP (if you didn't
        understand anything, most likely the following <emphasis>is applicable
        to you too</emphasis>) you have to enable Joomla!'s FTP layer.
        Otherwise Joomla! won't be able to write the files to its directories
        and installation will fail.</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Go to <guimenu>Site</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Global
            Configuration</guimenuitem> menu item from the top menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <guilabel>Server</guilabel> tab</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Set <guilabel>Enable FTP</guilabel> to Yes</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the <guilabel>FTP Host</guilabel> try using
            <option>127.0.0.1</option> or <option>localhost</option> or the
            FTP hostname assigned by your host</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the <guilabel>FTP Username</guilabel> and <guilabel>FTP
            Password</guilabel> fields provide the FTP username and password
            assigned by your host</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the <guilabel>FTP Root</guilabel> you have to type in the
            FTP path to your site's root. Here is the easy way to find it
            using <link
            xlink:href="http://filezilla-project.org/download.php">FileZilla</link>:</para>

            <para>Connect to your site using FileZilla. Navigate inside the
            folder Joomla! is installed in. Usually it's a directory named
            <filename>public_html</filename>, <filename>htdocs</filename>,
            <filename>www</filename> or something similar. If unsure don't ask
            us, ask your host. Now, on the right-hand pane you will find the
            FTP path. Most likely it will look something like
            <filename>/public_html</filename>. Copy this and paste it into the
            FTP Root text box in your Joomla!'s Global Configuration
            page.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Save your Global Configuration. If you got everything
            correctly, you should see a message that your configuration was
            saved. If you see an error message please seek assistance on the
            <link xlink:href="http://forum.joomla.org">Joomla!
            Forum</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <bridgehead>Manual installation</bridgehead>

        <para>Sometimes <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> is unable to properly
        extract ZIP archives due to technical limitations on your server. In
        this case, you can follow a manual installation procedure.</para>

        <para>First, you have to extract the installation ZIP file in a
        subdirectory named <filename>akeeba</filename> on your local PC. Then,
        upload the entire subdirectory inside your site's temporary directory.
        At this point, there should be a subdirectory named
        <filename>akeeba</filename> inside your site's temporary directory
        which contains all of the ZIP package's files.</para>

        <para>If you are unsure where your site's temporary directory is
        located, you can look it up by going to the <guimenuitem>Global
        Configuration</guimenuitem>, click on the <guilabel>Server</guilabel>
        tab and take a look at the <guilabel>Path to Temp-folder</guilabel>
        setting. The default setting is the <filename>tmp</filename> directory
        under your site's root. Rarely, especially on automated installations
        using Fantastico, this might have been assigned the system-wide
        <filename>/tmp</filename> directory. In this case, please consult your
        host for instructions on how to upload files inside this directory, or
        read the instructions above about changing your
        <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> temporary directory back to the default
        location and making it writable.</para>

        <para>Assuming that you are past this uploading step, click on the
        <guimenu>Extensions</guimenu>,
        <guimenuitem>Install/Uninstall</guimenuitem> (Joomla! 1.5) or
        <guimenu>Extensions</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Manage</guimenuitem>
        (Joomla! 1.6 users) link on the top menu. In this page, locate the
        <guibutton>Install Directory</guibutton> edit box in the
        <guilabel>Install from Directory</guilabel> area. It is already filled
        in with the absolute path to your temporary directory, for example
        <filename>/var/www/joomla/tmp</filename>. Please append
        <filename>/akeeba</filename> to it. As per our example, it should look
        something like <filename>/var/www/joomla/tmp/akeeba</filename>. Then,
        click on the <guibutton>Install</guibutton> button.</para>

        <bridgehead>Still problems?</bridgehead>

        <para>If you still can't install Akeeba Subscriptions and you are
        receiving messages regarding unwritable directories, inability to move
        files or other similar file system related error messages, please do
        not ask us for support. These errors stem from your site set up and
        can best be resolved by asking for help in the <link
        xlink:href="http://forum.joomla.org">official
        <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> forums</link>. We can only support
        software we develop ourselves. Joomla!'s extension installer is
        certainly not developed by us and –believe us– we have tried to
        improve it and submitted some still pending patches to the Joomla!
        project. Therefore we regret that we have to say that, but we can't
        help you. Thank you for your understanding.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="setup-and-usage">
    <title>Initial set-up and usage</title>

    <section xml:id="how-subscriptions-work">
      <title>How subscriptions work</title>

      <para>Before you begin setting up Akeeba Subscriptions, you should be
      aware of the way subscriptions work under the hood. The most basic
      concept is the subscription level (referred to simply as Level from now
      on). This is what you are selling to your customers. Your customers buy
      a subscription to a Level. The composite piece of information containing
      the Level, payment information and expiration time is called a
      Subscription.</para>

      <para>When a user enters the subscription page, Akeeba Subscriptions
      first fetches the price associated with the Level your user wants to
      buy. It will then try to understand if there is an applicable discount.
      First, it will look into Upgrade definitions and produce a list of
      upgrade rules applicable for the user and the Level he wishes to buy. If
      there are multiple applicable upgrade rules, the one giving the maximum
      discount is elected. Next up, it takes a look at the coupon code, is
      supplied. If it is an active coupon and your user can use it to get a
      discount, the coupon's discount is calculated. In the case where there
      are two discounts, both an upgrade discount and a coupon discount, the
      highest one is elected. The level price minus the discount is called the
      Net Price.</para>

      <para>Right up, Akeeba Subscriptions will try to determine the
      applicable tax by going through all the tax rules. It will go through
      the tax rules and keep the one which is the closest match to the
      country, zip code, city and VIES registration status. If no match is
      found, Akeeba Subscriptions will select the tax rate defined in the very
      first tax rule you have defined. This is called the Tax Amount. The sum
      of the Net Price and Tax Amount is the Gross Amount and that's what the
      user will have to pay.</para>

      <para>When the user hits the Subscribe button, Akeeba Subscriptions will
      first check if this is a new or existing user. If it is a new user, it
      will create a new –but inactive– user account based on the information
      the user has supplied. A new, inactive subscription will be created for
      your user and he's redirected to the payment gateway. Exception: if you
      have an 100% or more discount (which means that the user shall pay
      nothing) he's not redirected to the payment gateway. Instead, he's
      redirected to the Subscription Confirmation page and his subscription
      becomes instantly active.</para>

      <para>Once the user finishes the payment, he's redirected to the
      Subscription Confirmation page. If he changes his mind and cancels the
      payment, he will be takes to the Subscription Cancellation page. The
      text on each page is determined by the relevant fields in the Level
      configuration.</para>

      <para>At the same time, your payment processor will send a post-back to
      your site, notifying Akeeba Subscriptions about the payment status. If
      the payment is marked as complete, the subscription is activated. Its
      start and expiration date are calculated based on the exact date and
      time that the payment post-back was received and the Level's configured
      length. If the associated user account was marked as blocked (inactive),
      it is activated. If any integrations are set up, they will run. For
      example, you may be adding users to JUGA groups upon a successful
      subscription.</para>

      <para>Based on the above, you need to configure the following –in the
      order shown– for Akeeba Subscriptions to work:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Configuration Options - well, that's just the currency you're
          selling in!</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Subscription Levels - the subscription products you are
          selling, i.e. your inventory</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Tax Rules - determine if the user has to be charged taxes over
          the subscription amount and how much that will be</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Upgrade rules - (optional) discounts based on what other
          products the user has bought and how long he's been a subscriber to
          them</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Coupons - (optional) discount codes used for promotions</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Alternatively, you can import Subscription Levels and Coupons from
      other subscription systems instead of manually defining them.</para>

      <para>The sections below will tell you how to go through each of these
      steps.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="configuration">
      <title>Configuration options</title>

      <para>Click on <guilabel>Configuration</guilabel> in the toolbar links
      area. The available options are:</para>

      <para><guilabel>Currency Options</guilabel></para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Currency code</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <link xlink:href="http://www.xe.com/iso4217.php">three
            letter ISO 4217 currency code</link>. Common values are EUR
            (Euro), USD (United States Dollar), GBP (Great Britain Pound), CAD
            (Canada Dollar), AUD (Australia Dollar), JPY (Japan Yen), CNY
            (China Yuan) and MXN (Mexico, Pesos). This is used on virtually
            all of the payment processors to notify them about the currency
            you're selling your goods in. Please remember that all of your
            payment processors must support the selected currency. Some
            payment processors only accept a subset of currencies, most
            usually only one of USD, GBP and EUR.</para>

            <para>Default: EUR (Euro)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Currency Symbol</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The currency symbol to be shown to your web visitors, e.g. €
            for Euro, £ for British Pound, $ for US/Australia/Canada Dollar or
            ¥ for Japan Yen. This is free form text used to prefix the prices.
            If your currency has no special symbol you can use text to
            describe it, or leave blank to completely omit the currency symbol
            display throughout the components.</para>

            <para>Default: € (Euro symbol)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para><guilabel>Front-end display</guilabel></para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Show steps bar</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Should we render the steps bar (1-2-3) on the top of the
            page?</para>

            <para>Default: Yes</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="subscription-levels">
      <title>Subscription Levels</title>

      <para>You can access this feature by clicking on <guilabel>Subscription
      Levels</guilabel> in the toolbar links area.</para>

      <para>Creating or editing a Subscription Level, you have these
      options:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Title</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>How the subscription will be presented to your users. We
            strongly suggest using all-capital letters and no spaces for
            easier administration, albeit you can really use anything you
            like.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Image</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select a picture to represent your subscription. The image
            must be located in your site's images/stories (Joomla! 1.5) or
            images (Joomla! 1.6) directory.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Subscription Length (days)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>How many days a subscription in this level lasts. Common
            values are 30 (one month), 180 (half a year) and 365 (one
            year).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Price</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The price of a subscription in this level. If you need to
            enter a decimal value, use a dot as the decimal separator. For
            example, 12.30 is valid, whereas 12,30 is INVALID and will be
            interpreted as 1230. Do NOT use a thousands separator. For example
            1000 is valid, whereas 1,000 is INVALID.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Slug</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The alias, used to construct the URL. Use only lowercase
            Latin characters without diacretics and accents, dashes and
            underscores. For example <option>uber-sub</option> is valid,
            whereas <option>über SUB</option> is INVALID.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Published</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Should it be shown to your users?</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Short Description</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A description of the subscription to show to your users.
            Keep it short (ca. 30 words or less) or it will overflow the
            boundaries of the subscription presentation areas in the
            front-end.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Message to show after successful sign-up</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The text in this area will be presented to the users after
            they successfully complete their payment. Use it to thank them for
            giving you their money and show them important information about
            their subscription, e.g. links to your support method, download
            links etc.</para>

            <warning>
              <para>Do not include any sensitive information (such as "secret"
              download links) as the content of this page can be directly
              accessed by a knowledgeable user by manipulating the URL. If you
              want to include such information, please use the Restricted
              Content plugin bundled with Akeeba Subscriptions to make sure
              that the information will only be shown to users holding a valid
              subscription.</para>
            </warning>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Message to show after sign-up cancellation</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The text in this area will be presented to the users after
            they cancel their payment (if your payment gateway supports this
            feature). This is your last attempt to changing your user's mind
            or have them give you feedback on the reasons they decided to not
            move forward with their subscription. Use it wisely and do not
            insult your users, please :)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="tax-rules">
      <title>Tax Rules</title>

      <para>You can access this feature by clicking on <guilabel>Tax
      Rules</guilabel> in the toolbar links area.</para>

      <para>Out of the box, Akeeba Subscriptions is set up to not apply any
      VAT or other tax at all. However, this is not what most users would
      like. Below we are providing the most common setups based on your
      business type. Our lawyers told us that we have to say this to you:
      Please note that we are not lawyers or tax technicians. As a result, our
      advice is based on our personal experience, may be flawed and in no way
      should be considered a legal or financial advice. Should you chose to
      use it you do so at your own risk. We strongly advise you to ask a
      qualified tax technician, lawyer or other relevant professional
      qualified by law to give you advice regarding tax laws. That said,
      here's the most common tax setups:</para>

      <bridgehead>Extra-EU businesses, e.g. US based</bridgehead>

      <para>Tax Rules determine if the user should be charged a tax amount on
      top of the regular price of the subscription level. If you do not wish
      to charge any taxes (e.g. you have already included any applicable taxes
      in your subscription price), you will still have to create a default
      rule with 0 tax charges. In order to do so, click on the New button,
      select the "- Select -" option in the Country drop-down and set the tax
      rate to 0, then click on Save. Now you have created a catch-all rule
      with 0% tax. Likewise, if you want to charge all users a flat tax rate,
      say 18%, do the same thing, but set the tax rate to your desired
      percentage, in our case 18 (note: without the % sign!) and click on
      Save.</para>

      <bridgehead>Intra-EU businesses with a VIES registered VAT number, or
      extra-EU businesses with an EU VAT number</bridgehead>

      <para>If you are a business based in the European Union with a
      VIES-registered VAT number you have to create a total of 30 rules to
      conform to the overcomplicated EU tax regulations. First, create a
      default rule with 0% tax as noted above. Then do the same thing, but set
      the <guilabel>VIES Reg</guilabel> option to Yes and the tax rate to 0%.
      Now create new tax rules for each one of these countries, <guilabel>VIES
      Reg</guilabel> set to No and tax rate set to your local VAT tax rate
      (e.g. 23% for Greece): United Kingdom, Austria, Belgium, Bulgaria,
      Cyprus, Czech Republic, Germany, Greece, Denmark, Estonia, Spain,
      Finland, France, Hungary, Ireland, Italy, Lithuania, Luxembourg, Latvia,
      Malta, Netherlands, Poland, Portugal, Romania, Sweden, Slovenia,
      Slovakia. For the country of your business (e.g. Greece for a
      Greece-based business) create on more rule with <guilabel>VIES
      Reg</guilabel> set to Yes and the tax rate set to your local VAT tax
      rate (e.g. 23% for Greece). This way, the following happens:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the customer is extra-EU he will be charged no VAT</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the customer is an intra-EU business, he will be charged no
          VAT (he's liable to VAT on his local tax authorities, not your
          country's tax authorities)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the customer is intra-EU, but not a business with a
          VIES-registered VAT number, he's paying VAT.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the customer is coming from your own country, you are
          charging him with VAT no matter what.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Do note that the same setup is required if you are an extra-EU
      business –e.g. US-based– with an EU VAT ID (it's in the format
      EU012345678). In this case, you have no EU country of residence, so you
      can skip the last tax rule mentioned above.</para>

      <bridgehead>Intra-EU businesses without a VIES-registered VAT
      number</bridgehead>

      <para>Please ask your lawyer whether it's legal for you to sell
      subscriptions to residents of a country other than yours. There is a gap
      in the EU directives regarding that case, therefore we can't provide you
      with even semi-accurate tax setup information within any stretch of
      imagination.</para>

      <bridgehead>Tax Rule options</bridgehead>

      <para>Each tax rule has the following options:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Country</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Which country this tax rule is applicable in. If empty (the
            "- Select -" pseudo-option of the country list) it applies to all
            countries.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>State</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Which state this tax rule is applicable in. Note: only US
            and Canada states and provinces can be selected. If left empty
            (the N/A option) it applies to all states.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>City</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Which city this tax rule is applicable in. Do note that the
            spelling of the city must match, but it's case insensitive. This
            means that <option>new york</option>, <option>NEW YORK</option>
            and <option>New York</option> are equivalent. Leave blank to match
            all cities.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>VIES Reg</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If set to Yes, the tax rule matches only those clients with
            a valid, VIES registered EU VAT number. If you don't know what
            VIES registration is, <link
            xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/taxation_customs/taxation/vat/traders/vat_number/index_en.htm">read
            this</link>. You can verify if a VAT number of an EU resident or
            EU registered business is also VIES registered through EU's <link
            xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/taxation_customs/vies/">official
            web application on Europa.eu</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Tax Rate</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The tax rate percentage. If you need to enter decimal
            digits, use a dot not a comma. For example, <option>17.5</option>
            is valid, <option>17,5</option> is INVALID. Do NOT type the
            percentage sign. For example, <option>23</option> is valid,
            <option>23%</option> is INVALID. The percentage is always implied,
            that's why it's printed after the field's contents.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Enabled</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If set to Yes, the VAT Rule will be applied, otherwise it
            will be ignored (as if it weren't set at all)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="upgrade-rules">
      <title>Upgrade Rules</title>

      <para>You can access this feature by clicking on
      <guilabel>Upgrades</guilabel> in the toolbar links area.</para>

      <para>This feature allows you to create automatically applied discount
      rules to reward your loyal customers by giving them a discount. If you
      are not sure this is what you want to do, I strongly suggest reading
      Seth Godin's "<link
      xlink:href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2011/02/how-should-you-treat-your-best-customers.html">How
      should you treat your best customers?</link>" and view <link
      xlink:href="http://www.attorneymarketing.com/2010/04/25/seth-godin-explains-how-to-build-a-tribe-of-loyal-clients/">this
      video of his</link> where he explains his ideas on small businesses even
      more clearly.</para>

      <para>Each Upgrade rule has the following options:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Title</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Just a title to remind you of what this upgrade rule
            does</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Published</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If set to No, it won't be taken into account during a new
            subscription's price calculation</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>From level</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The subscription level for which the user must already have
            a valid subscription in order for the upgrade rule to take
            effect</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>To Level</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The subscription level which the user is currently trying to
            subscribe to and onto which the discount will be applied</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Min. Presence</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The minimum number of days the user has to have a valid
            subscription to From Level for this rule to be applied</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Max. Presence</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The maximum number of days the user has to have a valid
            subscription to From Level for this rule to be applied</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Discount Type</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If it's Value, the Value field contains currency, e.g. if
            you're using Euros and type a value of 20 then 20 Euros will be
            subtracted from the price. If its Percent, then the Value field
            contains a percentage, e.g. if you type a value of 20 then a 20%
            discount will be applied to the price.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Value</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>See above.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>Practical examples of upgrade rules:</para>

      <para>You want to give a 30% discount to users with a SUB1 annual
      subscription if they renew up to 30 days before their subscription
      expiration. Both levels set to SUB1, min presence is set to 0, max
      presence is set to 335 (one year is 365 days, minus 30 days, equals 335
      days), discount type Percent, value 30.</para>

      <para>You want to give a 15% discount to users with a SUB1 annual
      subscription if they renew during the last 30 days of their
      subscription. Both levels set to SUB1, min presence is set to 335 (one
      year is 365 days, minus 30 days, equals 335 days), max presence set to
      365 (one full year) discount type Percent, value 15.</para>

      <para>You want to give a 10 Euro discount to users with a SUB1 annual
      subscription who are now buying a SUB2 subscription. From Level set to
      SUB1, To Level set to SUB2, min presence set to 0, max presence set to
      365 (one year), discount set to Value, value set to 10.</para>

      <para>You want users buying both SUB1 and SUB2 to have a 10 Euro
      discount. First, create a rule like in the previous example. Then create
      another rule with From Level set to SUB2, To Level set to SUB1, min
      presence set to 0, max presence set to 365, discount set to Value, value
      set to 10. This way, whichever subscription they buy first, they'll get
      the discount when they buy the other subscription as well.</para>

      <para>You want to give a complimentary (free) SUB3 subscription to users
      who have already bought SUB1 and SUB2: you can't do that with Upgrade
      Rules, as you can not combine multiple subscriptions in a single rule.
      Instead, use a coupon code with 100% discount and show this coupon code
      only to subscribers who have already bought a SUB1 and SUB2 subscription
      using the Restricted Content plugin bundled with Akeeba
      Subscriptions.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="coupons">
      <title>Coupons</title>

      <para>You can access this feature by clicking on
      <guilabel>Coupons</guilabel> in the toolbar links area.</para>

      <para>This feature allows you to create discount coupon codes. When a
      user enters a valid coupon code during registration, it's subtracted
      from the price of his subscription. You can let coupons work on specific
      subscriptions, specific users, for a predefined time period or even for
      a predefined number of times before becoming inactive. You can even
      create 100% discount coupons for giveaways or other similar promotional
      reasons.</para>

      <para>Each coupon supports the following fields:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Title</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A descriptive title for your coupon. It is only displayed to
            you, it is not displayed to your users.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Coupon code</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The coupon code which the user has to enter in order to
            receive the discount. Very important: coupon codes are case
            insensitive, therefore it's best to type them in all capital
            letters. Moreover, we suggest using only capital Latin letters
            without accents or diacretics and numbers, so that all users can
            type them in using their keyboard.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Discount type</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>You can either specify Percent (give an X% discount over the
            price) or Value (deducts X from the price). It works in
            conjunction with the Value field below. For example, if you are
            using Euros as your currency, you set Value here and type in a
            value of 10, the coupon gives 10 Euro discount.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Discount value</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>See above</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Published</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Set to Yes for the coupon to become active</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Hits</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This is the number of times this coupon has been
            used.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Valid from</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>When the coupon will become active (note: the date is
            expressed in the GMT/UTC timezone). Leave blank or set to
            0000-00-00 00:00:00 to make the coupon active right now. Note: a
            published coupon will not be taken into account before its Valid
            From date.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Valid to</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>When the coupon will become inactive (note: the date is
            expressed in the GMT/UTC timezone). Leave blank or set to
            0000-00-00 00:00:00 to let Akeeba Subscriptions ignore this field
            and let the coupon active until you manually unpublish it. Note: a
            published coupon will not be taken into account after its Valid To
            date.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Limit to a specific user</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click on <guibutton>Select</guibutton> to pick a user for
            which the coupon will be active. For all other users the coupon
            will have no effect. Leave blank to let all users –even new ones–
            to use the coupon.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Subscription Levels</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Choose the subscription levels which the coupon code can be
            applied to. Leave it blank (or make sure that only the <option>-
            Select -</option> pseudo-option is selected) to let Akeeba
            Subscriptions apply the coupon to all current and future
            subscription levels you are offering on your site.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Hits limit</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If it is greater than zero, the coupon can be used up to
            this number of times before it becomes inactive. In other words,
            when the Hits counter becomes equal to Hits Limit, the coupon can
            no longer be used by anyone. Leave it blank to not apply any such
            limit.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="subscriptions-management">
      <title>Subscriptions management</title>

      <para>You can access this feature by clicking on
      <guilabel>Subscriptions</guilabel> in the toolbar links area.</para>

      <para>This is a standard Joomla! administrator page which needs no
      explanation.</para>

      <para>The icons on the left hand side of the user information are
      Gravatars. If the user has linked a Gravatar to their email address, it
      is displayed next to their name, otherwise a default avatar (head-shaped
      cut out) is displayed.</para>

      <para>In order to edit a subscription, click on the leftmost column (the
      numeric ID) of the subscription record. Clicking on the other links will
      edit the respective item, i.e. clicking on the subscription level will
      open the subscription level editor.</para>

      <para>You can use the <guibutton>Run Integrations</guibutton> button any
      time in order to have Akeeba Subscriptions re-process all integrations
      with third party components. This is useful when you suspect an
      integration has gone wrong, you changed the options in an integration
      plugin or you just imported a large number of subscriptions.</para>

      <para>Using the CSV button allows you to export the current view into a
      CSV file for further processing in a spreadsheet application such as
      Microsoft Office Excel, Apple Numbers or OpenOffice.org Calc. Do note
      that the full set of raw data is dumped to the CSV file.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="frotn-end-items">
      <title>Front-end items</title>

      <para>There are four types of front-end menu items you can
      create:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Subscribe • Specific Level</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Allows you to create a menu link to the subscription page of
            a specific Subscription Level</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Subscription Levels • Awesome Layout</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Presents a list of all available subscription levels in a
            comparison table, using CSS3 styling. It's the most eye-catching
            presentation layout and it's best to use only if you have a small
            number of subscription levels (4 to 5)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Subscription Levels • All Levels</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Presents a list of all available subscription levels as a
            two column list of boxes. It is a relatively dull presentation
            mode, but is suitable for a very large number of subscription
            levels (over 6)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>My subscriptions • All of my subscriptions</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Think of it as a kind of "My Account" page. It shows the
            user all of his subscriptions and allows him to review the
            information on each one of them, as well as renew them.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>The subscription page defines two module positions where you can
      publish modules to further expand the information presented on the page.
      Publishing modules in the <option>akeebasubscriptionsheader</option>
      position will make them appear at the very top of the page, right above
      the Steps bar. That's a good place to publish information about SSL
      security or banners about your latest special offers. Publishing modules
      in the <option>akeebasubscriptionsfooter</option> position will make
      them appear right after the end of the subscription form. This is a good
      place to put a custom HTML module with links to your terms of service,
      business contact information, etc.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="importing-from-other-components">
      <title>Importing from other components</title>

      <para>Most likely you are already using a subscriptions system and
      wouldn't like to have to manually import all of your subscriptions to
      Akeeba Subscriptions. That's why we are offering an automated import
      feature. You can access it from Akeeba Subscription's dashboard page, by
      clicking on the Operations tab, and then on
      <guibutton>Import</guibutton>.</para>

      <para>The options are:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>AMBRA.Subscriptions</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Imports subscription levels and subscriptions from
            Dioscouri's AMBRA Subscriptions (a.k.a. AMBRA.subs)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>AMBRA.Subscriptions with PayPal with VAT plugin</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you are using AMBRA.subs with my modified "PayPal with
            VAT" payment plugin and the customizations for integrating coupons
            into AMBRA.subs, you can click on this option. It will import
            subscription levels, subscriptions and any coupon codes defined.
            Moreover, it will also import the extra data stored per user, e.g.
            their address and VAT number.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <warning>
        <para>Importing from other components will DELETE AND REPLACE ANY AND
        ALL EXISTING DATA IN AKEEBA SUBSCRIPTIONS. There is NO TURNING BACK.
        Do NOT use this option after you have been using Akeeba Subscriptions
        and have new subscribers on your site.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>Please remember to review your Subscription Levels after import.
      Most notably, the text of the subscription completion and subscription
      cancellation pages will be missing from all subscription levels.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="plugins">
    <title>Payment methods, integrations and plugins</title>

    <para>Akeeba Subscriptions is designed to be a modular system, powered by
    standard Joomla! plugins. Using plugins you can add payment methods as
    well as integration with third party software. Moreover, core
    functionality of Akeeba Subscriptions (like sending out emails upon
    subscription or email reminders for subscription expiration) is take care
    of by plugins. This documentation chapter will guide you through the
    details of each plugin.</para>

    <section xml:id="payment-plugins">
      <title>Payment methods</title>

      <para>All payment methods are standard Joomla! plugins, belonging to the
      <option>akpayment</option> group. If you want to enable a payment
      method, just publish the relevant plugin.</para>

      <section xml:id="payment-paypal">
        <title>Paypal</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions Payment - Paypal</guilabel></para>

        <para>This payment method integrates the standard PayPal Website
        Payments service, available without any setup fee to all verified
        PayPal clients. In other words, that's the standard way to use PayPal
        as your payment processor. The options you have in this plugin
        are:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Payment option title</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Leave blank to use "PayPal" or type in a custom name to
              show to your customer's, e.g. "PayPal, bank account or Credit
              Card"</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Merchant ID</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Your PayPal email address or your secure merchant ID (if
              PayPal has assigned you with one)</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Secure POST</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>If enabled, the verification postback to PayPal will be
              over an SSL connection. In order for this to work, your host
              needs to support SSL connections using cURL to PayPal's IP
              address block.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Sandbox</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>When enabled, transactions are processed by PayPal
              Sandbox, i.e. PayPal's testing mode. This is designed for
              integration tests, BEFORE going live with your site. <emphasis
              role="bold">NEVER, EVER, NO MATTER WHAT YOU DO, SHOULD YOU NOT
              ENABLE THIS ON PRODUCTION SITES! IF YOU DO, YOU WILL LOSE MONEY
              AND/OR CUSTOMERS.</emphasis></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Sandbox merchant</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The dummy merchant email used with PayPal's
              Sandbox.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>PayPal Callback Text</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>(optional) Normally, when the user completes the payment,
              PayPal shows him a button with the default label "Return to
              Merchant". If you type in something in here, it will be shown on
              that button instead of the default label. For example, you can
              type in something like "Return to Example.com"</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Custom Header Image</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>(optional) The URL to an image to be shown on PayPal's
              checkout page header. It'd better be hosted on an HTTPS URL,
              otherwise your customers will get a warning about insecure
              content on their browser.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Header Background Color</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The hex code of PayPal checkout page's header background
              color. For example, white is FFFFFF (note: there is no # sign in
              front of the hex color code!)</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Header Border Color</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The hex code of PayPal checkout page's header border
              color. For example, light gray is CCCCCC (note: there is no #
              sign in front of the hex color code!)</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="payment-none">
        <title>None</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions Payment - None</guilabel></para>

        <para>This is a dummy payment plugin which immediately activates a
        subscription without payment.</para>

        <warning>
          <para>DO NOT USE THIS ON PRODUCTION SITES. IT IS MEANT FOR TESTING
          PURPOSES ONLY. ENABLING IT ON A PRODUCTION SITE ALLOWS ANYONE,
          INCLUDING UNREGISTERED USERS, TO SUBSCRIBE TO ANY SUBSCRIPTION THEY
          WANT <emphasis role="bold">WITHOUT PAYING ANYTHING AT
          ALL</emphasis>. You have been strongly warned.</para>
        </warning>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="payment-offline">
        <title>Off-line</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions Payment - Off-line</guilabel></para>

        <para>This is a payment plugin which lets your users complete their
        payment off-line, e.g. through bank (wire) transfer, money check,
        Western Union or any other means of payment that you allow. It works
        very simply: it just presents your user with a customizable
        instructions message. In that message you can use the variables
        <replaceable>{SUBSCRIPTION}</replaceable> to display the subscription
        ID and <replaceable>{AMOUNT}</replaceable> to display the amount due.
        Please use all caps for these variables and include the curly
        braces.</para>

        <para>Once the user effects the payment, simply go to your
        Subscriptions view, enable his subscriptions and set the payment
        status to "Completed". That's all!</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="plugins-integration">
      <title>Integration with third party software</title>

      <para>One of the most important aspects about subscription systems is
      their ability to integrate with third party software. A subscription all
      by itself means pretty much nothing. It's just a "flag". The added value
      is when this subscription allows the user holding it to actually do
      something on the site. At this point in time, there are only a handful
      of integrations. If you are interested in more integrations let us know
      and we'll add them to our implementation to-do list.</para>

      <para>All integrations with third party applications are standard
      Joomla! plugins, published in the <option>akeebasubs</option>
      group.</para>

      <section xml:id="integration-juga">
        <title>JUGA Integration</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions - JUGA Integration</guilabel></para>

        <para>This integration plugin allows you to add and remove users from
        JUGA groups based on their subscription status. Please note that this
        is a smart integration; instead of adding users when a subscription
        goes active and removing them when a subscription goes inactive,
        Akeeba Subscriptions plugins take a look at all of the user's active
        and inactive subscriptions and decide which groups the user should be
        added to or removed from. The idea is this:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>All groups to be added to, based on active subscriptions of
            the user, are assembled to the ADD list.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>All groups to be removed from, based on inactive
            subscriptions of the user, are assembled to the REMOVE
            list.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If a JUGA group appears in both the ADD and REMOVE list, it
            is deleted from the REMOVE list. In other words "add" trumps
            "delete". In order to understand this further, here's the deal. If
            one subscription with access to a JUGA group expires, but another
            subscription granting access to the very same group is still
            active, the user's access to this group must remain active.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>The plugin has these options:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Add to JUGA groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This is a list for assigning subscription levels to JUGA
              groups. When a user has an active subscription to the specified
              level, he'll be added to the JUGA group mentioned on the right
              hand of the equal sign. Each assignment is done like
              this:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3</programlisting>

              <para>Where LEVEL1 is the Title of the subscription level and
              Group 1, Group 2 and Group 3 are the names of the JUGA groups
              you want to add a user to when he subscribes. If you want to
              assign multiple subscription levels to multiple groups, you have
              to do something like that (separate multiple lines with a single
              press of the ENTER key on your keyboard):</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 4,Group 1</programlisting>

              <para>You can also use the numeric IDs of subscription levels or
              JUGA groups instead of their titles. However, we consider
              working with numeric IDs very counter-intuitive.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Remove from JUGA groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Likewise, this is the list of the JUGA groups to remove a
              user from when his subscription to the specified level is no
              longer active. Do note that you can specify a different set of
              groups to remove the user from than the ones you are adding him
              to. For example:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 1</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>In this example, together with the rules displayed in "Add to
        JUGA groups", when a subscription to the LEVEL1 level expires, the
        user will still belong to JUGA's Group 3, as it's not removed from his
        account; only Group 1 and Group 2 are removed. Likewise, if the user
        has an expired LEVEL1 subscription and an active LEVEL2 subscription
        he'll now belong to Group 2 and Group 3: Group 3 because it's not
        removed when his subscription expires and Group 2 because his active
        LEVEL2 subscription suggests that he should be granted Group 2 access
        despite his expired LEVEL1 subscription.</para>

        <para>If you find this hard to understand, join the club. ACLs are not
        meant to be easy to setup or understand. It's a power feature and, as
        such, poses a great difficulty to even the most seasoned web site
        integrators. Take your time and experiment on a dev copy of your site
        before going live.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="integration-ninjaboard">
        <title>NinjaBoard Integration</title>

        <note>
          <para>This feature is only available in the Professional
          edition</para>
        </note>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions - NinjaBoard Integration</guilabel></para>

        <para>This integration plugin allows you to add and remove users from
        NinjaBoard groups based on their subscription status. This allows you
        to control view/post/attachments access to your NinjaBoard forums
        based on a user's subscription status and can form the basis of a
        commercial support forum, like the one we use at
        AkeebaBackup.com.</para>

        <para>Please note that this is a smart integration, exactly as
        described in the JUGA plugin earlier in this documentation; instead of
        adding users when a subscription goes active and removing them when a
        subscription goes inactive, Akeeba Subscriptions plugins take a look
        at all of the user's active and inactive subscriptions and decide
        which groups the user should be added to or removed from.</para>

        <para>The plugin has these options:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Add to NinjaBoard groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This is a list for assigning subscription levels to
              NinjaBoard groups. When a user has an active subscription to the
              specified level, he'll be added to the NinjaBoard group
              mentioned on the right hand of the equal sign. Each assignment
              is done like this:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3</programlisting>

              <para>Where LEVEL1 is the Title of the subscription level and
              Group 1, Group 2 and Group 3 are the names of the NinjaBoard
              groups you want to add a user to when he subscribes. If you want
              to assign multiple subscription levels to multiple groups, you
              have to do something like that (separate multiple lines with a
              single press of the ENTER key on your keyboard):</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 4,Group 1</programlisting>

              <para>You can also use the numeric IDs of subscription levels or
              NinjaBoard groups instead of their titles. However, we consider
              working with numeric IDs very counter-intuitive.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Remove from NinjaBoard groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Likewise, this is the list of the NinjaBoard groups to
              remove a user from when his subscription to the specified level
              is no longer active. Do note that you can specify a different
              set of groups to remove the user from than the ones you are
              adding him to. For example:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 1</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>In this example, together with the rules displayed in "Add to
        NinjaBoard groups", when a subscription to the LEVEL1 level expires,
        the user will still belong to NinjaBoard's Group 3, as it's not
        removed from his account; only Group 1 and Group 2 are removed.
        Likewise, if the user has an expired LEVEL1 subscription and an active
        LEVEL2 subscription he'll now belong to Group 2 and Group 3: Group 3
        because it's not removed when his subscription expires and Group 2
        because his active LEVEL2 subscription suggests that he should be
        granted Group 2 access despite his expired LEVEL1 subscription.</para>

        <para>If you find this hard to understand, join the club. ACLs are not
        meant to be easy to setup or understand. It's a power feature and, as
        such, poses a great difficulty to even the most seasoned web site
        integrators. Take your time and experiment on a dev copy of your site
        before going live.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="integration-joomla">
        <title>Joomla! 1.6 User Groups Integration</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions - Joomla! 1.6 Usergroups Integration</guilabel></para>

        <para>This integration plugin allows you to add and remove users from
        Joomla! 1.6 groups based on their subscription status. This allows you
        to fully utilize Joomla! 1.6's built-in ACL capabilities on compatible
        extensions.</para>

        <para>Please note that this is a smart integration, exactly as
        described in the JUGA plugin earlier in this documentation; instead of
        adding users when a subscription goes active and removing them when a
        subscription goes inactive, Akeeba Subscriptions plugins take a look
        at all of the user's active and inactive subscriptions and decide
        which groups the user should be added to or removed from.</para>

        <para>The plugin has these options:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Add to Joomla! 1.6 groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This is a list for assigning subscription levels to
              NinjaBoard groups. When a user has an active subscription to the
              specified level, he'll be added to the NinjaBoard group
              mentioned on the right hand of the equal sign. Each assignment
              is done like this:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3</programlisting>

              <para>Where LEVEL1 is the Title of the subscription level and
              Group 1, Group 2 and Group 3 are the names of the NinjaBoard
              groups you want to add a user to when he subscribes. If you want
              to assign multiple subscription levels to multiple groups, you
              have to do something like that (separate multiple lines with a
              single press of the ENTER key on your keyboard):</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 4,Group 1</programlisting>

              <para>You can also use the numeric IDs of subscription levels or
              NinjaBoard groups instead of their titles. However, we consider
              working with numeric IDs very counter-intuitive.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Remove from Joomla! 1.6 groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Likewise, this is the list of the NinjaBoard groups to
              remove a user from when his subscription to the specified level
              is no longer active. Do note that you can specify a different
              set of groups to remove the user from than the ones you are
              adding him to. For example:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 1</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>In this example, together with the rules displayed in "Add to
        NinjaBoard groups", when a subscription to the LEVEL1 level expires,
        the user will still belong to Joomla!'s Group 3, as it's not removed
        from his account; only Group 1 and Group 2 are removed. Likewise, if
        the user has an expired LEVEL1 subscription and an active LEVEL2
        subscription he'll now belong to Group 2 and Group 3: Group 3 because
        it's not removed when his subscription expires and Group 2 because his
        active LEVEL2 subscription suggests that he should be granted Group 2
        access despite his expired LEVEL1 subscription.</para>

        <para>If you find this hard to understand, join the club. ACLs are not
        meant to be easy to setup or understand. It's a power feature and, as
        such, poses a great difficulty to even the most seasoned web site
        integrators. Take your time and experiment on a dev copy of your site
        before going live.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="integration-k2">
        <title>K2 Integration</title>

        <note>
          <para>This feature is only available in the Professional
          edition</para>
        </note>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions - K2 Integration</guilabel></para>

        <para>This integration plugin allows you to add and remove users from
        K2 1.6 groups based on their subscription status. This allows you to
        fully utilize K2's limited ACL capabilities (basically, just control
        front-end editing).</para>

        <warning>
          <para>K2 only allows a user to belong to one and only one group.
          This means that only the latest subscription's K2 group will be
          applied to your user if he holds several subscriptions.</para>
        </warning>

        <para>The plugin has these options:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Add to K2 groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This is a list for assigning subscription levels to
              NinjaBoard groups. When a user has an active subscription to the
              specified level, he'll be added to the NinjaBoard group
              mentioned on the right hand of the equal sign. Each assignment
              is done like this:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1</programlisting>

              <para>Where LEVEL1 is the Title of the subscription level and
              Group 1 is the names of the K2 group you want to add a user to
              when he subscribes. If you want to assign multiple subscription
              levels to multiple groups, you have to do something like that
              (separate multiple lines with a single press of the ENTER key on
              your keyboard):</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 3</programlisting>

              <para>You can also use the numeric IDs of subscription levels or
              K2 groups instead of their titles. However, we consider working
              with numeric IDs very counter-intuitive.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Remove from K2 groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Likewise, this is the list of the K2 groups to remove a
              user from when his subscription to the specified level is no
              longer active. Do note that you can specify a different set of
              groups to remove the user from than the ones you are adding him
              to. For example:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 3</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="integration-docman">
        <title>DOCman Integration</title>

        <note>
          <para>This feature is only available in the Professional
          edition</para>
        </note>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions - DOCman Integration</guilabel></para>

        <para>This integration plugin allows you to add and remove users from
        DOCman groups based on their subscription status. This allows you to
        control downloads/uploads to your DOCman downloads based on a user's
        subscription status and can form the basis of a commercial file
        distribution system.</para>

        <para>Please note that this is a smart integration, exactly as
        described in the JUGA plugin earlier in this documentation; instead of
        adding users when a subscription goes active and removing them when a
        subscription goes inactive, Akeeba Subscriptions plugins take a look
        at all of the user's active and inactive subscriptions and decide
        which groups the user should be added to or removed from.</para>

        <para>The plugin has these options:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Add to DOCman groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This is a list for assigning subscription levels to DOCman
              groups. When a user has an active subscription to the specified
              level, he'll be added to the DOCman group mentioned on the right
              hand of the equal sign. Each assignment is done like
              this:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3</programlisting>

              <para>Where LEVEL1 is the Title of the subscription level and
              Group 1, Group 2 and Group 3 are the names of the DOCman groups
              you want to add a user to when he subscribes. If you want to
              assign multiple subscription levels to multiple groups, you have
              to do something like that (separate multiple lines with a single
              press of the ENTER key on your keyboard):</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 4,Group 1</programlisting>

              <para>You can also use the numeric IDs of subscription levels or
              DOCman groups instead of their titles. However, we consider
              working with numeric IDs very counter-intuitive.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Remove from DOCman groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Likewise, this is the list of the DOCman groups to remove
              a user from when his subscription to the specified level is no
              longer active. Do note that you can specify a different set of
              groups to remove the user from than the ones you are adding him
              to. For example:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 1</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>In this example, together with the rules displayed in "Add to
        DOCman groups", when a subscription to the LEVEL1 level expires, the
        user will still belong to DOCman Group 3, as it's not removed from his
        account; only Group 1 and Group 2 are removed. Likewise, if the user
        has an expired LEVEL1 subscription and an active LEVEL2 subscription
        he'll now belong to Group 2 and Group 3: Group 3 because it's not
        removed when his subscription expires and Group 2 because his active
        LEVEL2 subscription suggests that he should be granted Group 2 access
        despite his expired LEVEL1 subscription.</para>

        <para>If you find this hard to understand, join the club. ACLs are not
        meant to be easy to setup or understand. It's a power feature and, as
        such, poses a great difficulty to even the most seasoned web site
        integrators. Take your time and experiment on a dev copy of your site
        before going live.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="integration-jce">
        <title>JCE Integration</title>

        <note>
          <para>This feature is only available in the Professional
          edition</para>
        </note>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions - JCE Integration</guilabel></para>

        <para>This integration plugin allows you to add and remove users from
        JCE (Joomla! Content Editor) groups based on their subscription
        status. This allows you to control the editing permissions of
        individual users based on their subscription status.</para>

        <para>Please note that this is a smart integration, exactly as
        described in the JUGA plugin earlier in this documentation; instead of
        adding users when a subscription goes active and removing them when a
        subscription goes inactive, Akeeba Subscriptions plugins take a look
        at all of the user's active and inactive subscriptions and decide
        which groups the user should be added to or removed from.</para>

        <para>The plugin has these options:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Add to JCE groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This is a list for assigning subscription levels to JCE
              groups. When a user has an active subscription to the specified
              level, he'll be added to the JCE group mentioned on the right
              hand of the equal sign. Each assignment is done like
              this:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3</programlisting>

              <para>Where LEVEL1 is the Title of the subscription level and
              Group 1, Group 2 and Group 3 are the names of the JCE groups you
              want to add a user to when he subscribes. If you want to assign
              multiple subscription levels to multiple groups, you have to do
              something like that (separate multiple lines with a single press
              of the ENTER key on your keyboard):</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 4,Group 1</programlisting>

              <para>You can also use the numeric IDs of subscription levels or
              JCE groups instead of their titles. However, we consider working
              with numeric IDs very counter-intuitive.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Remove from JCE groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Likewise, this is the list of the JCE groups to remove a
              user from when his subscription to the specified level is no
              longer active. Do note that you can specify a different set of
              groups to remove the user from than the ones you are adding him
              to. For example:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 1</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>In this example, together with the rules displayed in "Add to
        JCE groups", when a subscription to the LEVEL1 level expires, the user
        will still belong to JCE Group 3, as it's not removed from his
        account; only Group 1 and Group 2 are removed. Likewise, if the user
        has an expired LEVEL1 subscription and an active LEVEL2 subscription
        he'll now belong to Group 2 and Group 3: Group 3 because it's not
        removed when his subscription expires and Group 2 because his active
        LEVEL2 subscription suggests that he should be granted Group 2 access
        despite his expired LEVEL1 subscription.</para>

        <para>If you find this hard to understand, join the club. ACLs are not
        meant to be easy to setup or understand. It's a power feature and, as
        such, poses a great difficulty to even the most seasoned web site
        integrators. Take your time and experiment on a dev copy of your site
        before going live.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="integration-vm">
        <title>VirtueMart Integration</title>

        <note>
          <para>This feature is only available in the Professional
          edition</para>
        </note>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions - VirtueMart Integration</guilabel></para>

        <para>This integration plugin allows you to add and remove users from
        VirtueMart shopper groups based on their subscription status. This
        allows you to set special discounts to subscribers (e.g. a discount
        club) or other VirtueMart tricks which are based on the shopper groups
        a user belongs to.</para>

        <para>Please note that this is a smart integration, exactly as
        described in the JUGA plugin earlier in this documentation; instead of
        adding users when a subscription goes active and removing them when a
        subscription goes inactive, Akeeba Subscriptions plugins take a look
        at all of the user's active and inactive subscriptions and decide
        which groups the user should be added to or removed from.</para>

        <para>The plugin has these options:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Add to VirtueMart groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This is a list for assigning subscription levels to
              VirtueMart groups. When a user has an active subscription to the
              specified level, he'll be added to the VirtueMart group
              mentioned on the right hand of the equal sign. Each assignment
              is done like this:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3</programlisting>

              <para>Where LEVEL1 is the Title of the subscription level and
              Group 1, Group 2 and Group 3 are the names of the VirtueMart
              groups you want to add a user to when he subscribes. If you want
              to assign multiple subscription levels to multiple groups, you
              have to do something like that (separate multiple lines with a
              single press of the ENTER key on your keyboard):</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 4,Group 1</programlisting>

              <para>You can also use the numeric IDs of subscription levels or
              VirtueMart groups instead of their titles. However, we consider
              working with numeric IDs very counter-intuitive.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Remove from VirtueMart groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Likewise, this is the list of the VirtueMart groups to
              remove a user from when his subscription to the specified level
              is no longer active. Do note that you can specify a different
              set of groups to remove the user from than the ones you are
              adding him to. For example:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 1</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>In this example, together with the rules displayed in "Add to
        VirtueMart groups", when a subscription to the LEVEL1 level expires,
        the user will still belong to VirtueMart Group 3, as it's not removed
        from his account; only Group 1 and Group 2 are removed. Likewise, if
        the user has an expired LEVEL1 subscription and an active LEVEL2
        subscription he'll now belong to Group 2 and Group 3: Group 3 because
        it's not removed when his subscription expires and Group 2 because his
        active LEVEL2 subscription suggests that he should be granted Group 2
        access despite his expired LEVEL1 subscription.</para>

        <para>If you find this hard to understand, join the club. ACLs are not
        meant to be easy to setup or understand. It's a power feature and, as
        such, poses a great difficulty to even the most seasoned web site
        integrators. Take your time and experiment on a dev copy of your site
        before going live.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="integration-tienda">
        <title>Tienda Integration</title>

        <note>
          <para>This feature is only available in the Professional
          edition</para>
        </note>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions - Tienda Integration</guilabel></para>

        <para>This integration plugin allows you to add and remove users from
        Tienda shopper groups based on their subscription status. This allows
        you to set special discounts to subscribers (e.g. a discount club) or
        other Tienda tricks which are based on the shopper groups a user
        belongs to.</para>

        <para>Please note that this is a smart integration, exactly as
        described in the JUGA plugin earlier in this documentation; instead of
        adding users when a subscription goes active and removing them when a
        subscription goes inactive, Akeeba Subscriptions plugins take a look
        at all of the user's active and inactive subscriptions and decide
        which groups the user should be added to or removed from.</para>

        <para>The plugin has these options:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Add to Tienda groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This is a list for assigning subscription levels to Tienda
              groups. When a user has an active subscription to the specified
              level, he'll be added to the Tienda group mentioned on the right
              hand of the equal sign. Each assignment is done like
              this:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3</programlisting>

              <para>Where LEVEL1 is the Title of the subscription level and
              Group 1, Group 2 and Group 3 are the names of the Tienda groups
              you want to add a user to when he subscribes. If you want to
              assign multiple subscription levels to multiple groups, you have
              to do something like that (separate multiple lines with a single
              press of the ENTER key on your keyboard):</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 4,Group 1</programlisting>

              <para>You can also use the numeric IDs of subscription levels or
              Tienda groups instead of their titles. However, we consider
              working with numeric IDs very counter-intuitive.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Remove from Tienda groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Likewise, this is the list of the Tienda groups to remove
              a user from when his subscription to the specified level is no
              longer active. Do note that you can specify a different set of
              groups to remove the user from than the ones you are adding him
              to. For example:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 1</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>In this example, together with the rules displayed in "Add to
        Tienda groups", when a subscription to the LEVEL1 level expires, the
        user will still belong to Tienda Group 3, as it's not removed from his
        account; only Group 1 and Group 2 are removed. Likewise, if the user
        has an expired LEVEL1 subscription and an active LEVEL2 subscription
        he'll now belong to Group 2 and Group 3: Group 3 because it's not
        removed when his subscription expires and Group 2 because his active
        LEVEL2 subscription suggests that he should be granted Group 2 access
        despite his expired LEVEL1 subscription.</para>

        <para>If you find this hard to understand, join the club. ACLs are not
        meant to be easy to setup or understand. It's a power feature and, as
        such, poses a great difficulty to even the most seasoned web site
        integrators. Take your time and experiment on a dev copy of your site
        before going live.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="plugins-other">
      <title>Other plugins</title>

      <para>Akeeba Subscriptions comes with more standard Joomla! plugins
      which accomplish a variety of tasks, from email communications to
      content filtering.</para>

      <section xml:id="plugin-asexpirationcontrol">
        <title>Subscription expiration control</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <emphasis
        role="bold">System - Akeeba Subscriptions Expiration
        Control</emphasis></para>

        <para>Akeeba Subscriptions will automatically expire your users'
        subscriptions when they visit a page with an Akeeba Subscriptions
        module on your site after their subscription expiration date. However,
        if you want subscription expiration to be performed automatically, you
        need to publish this plugin. It will fire once per day, expiring
        subscriptions past their expiration date. We strongly recommend
        publishing this plugin at all times.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="plugin-subscriptionemails">
        <title>Subscription emails</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions - Emails</guilabel></para>

        <para>When this plugin is published, an email will be sent out to the
        user when any of these events takes place:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A new subscription is created</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The payment status changes, e.g. the user completes the
            payment, or a delayed payment is marked as completed or
            cancelled.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A subscription expires and becomes inactive</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <note>
          <para>This plugin uses Joomla!'s mail system. You have to ensure
          that your site can send out emails (e.g. use the Mass Mail feature
          to send a test email to Super Administrators) before activating this
          plugin.</para>
        </note>

        <para>We strongly recommend publishing this plugin at all
        times.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="plugin-asexpirationnotify">
        <title>Subscription expiration notification</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>System - Akeeba
        Subscriptions Expiration Notification</guilabel></para>

        <para>This plugin will notify a user 30 and 15 days before his
        subscription's expiration. These time limits are non-configurable in
        this release.</para>

        <note>
          <para>This plugin uses Joomla!'s mail system. You have to ensure
          that your site can send out emails (e.g. use the Mass Mail feature
          to send a test email to Super Administrators) before activating this
          plugin.</para>
        </note>

        <para>We strongly recommend publishing this plugin at all
        times.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="plugin-asrestricted">
        <title>Content restriction</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Content - Akeeba
        Subscriptions Restricted</guilabel></para>

        <para>This content plugin allows you to show parts of your content
        only to specific subscribers. This is a very powerful feature that
        allows you to alter the displayed content based on the user's
        subscription status.</para>

        <note>
          <para>It can not "hide" entire articles, e.g. not show them at all
          to non-subscribers. At best, only the title will be shown. If you
          want to completely hide articles and block unsubscribed user access
          to entire categories or sections in Joomla! 1.5 you will have to use
          an ACL solution, like Dioscouri's JUGA, NoixACL or similar.</para>

          <para>If you have Joomla! 1.6 or later you can use the bundled
          Joomla! 1.6 User Group integration plugin to automatically assign
          subscribers to Joomla!'s groups and then use Joomla!'s ACL feature
          to fine-tune which users have access to which articles.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Its syntax is:</para>

        <programlisting>{akeebasubs <replaceable>expression</replaceable>}Your content{/akeebasubs}</programlisting>

        <para>This means that "Your content" will only be displayed to users
        whose subscriptions satisfy the <replaceable>expression</replaceable>.
        In the simplest form, expression is just the name of a subscription
        level, e.g.</para>

        <programlisting>{akeebasubs LEVEL1}Your content{/akeebasubs}</programlisting>

        <para>If you want to present the content to someone who holds an
        active subscription to both LEVEL1 and LEVEL2, you can use the
        <option>&amp;&amp;</option> (logic and) operator:</para>

        <programlisting>{akeebasubs LEVEL1 <option>&amp;&amp;</option> LEVEL2}Your content{/akeebasubs}</programlisting>

        <para>Likewise, you can use the || (logic or) operator to present the
        content to anyone who has a subscription to any of LEVEL3 or LEVEL4
        levels:</para>

        <programlisting>{akeebasubs LEVEL3 <option>||</option> LEVEL4}Your content{/akeebasubs}</programlisting>

        <para>Important note: The logical OR consists of two "pipe" symbols.
        These are not the same as capital I! On a Mac's keyboard, the pipe
        symbol is present next to the ENTER key, accessible by pressing
        SHIFT-\. On most Windows/Linux machines, this key is usually somewhere
        near the ENTER key and is most likely accessible by pressing SHIFT-\
        as well.</para>

        <para>You can also negate the logic. For example, you can present the
        content to anyone having a subscription to neither LEVEL1 nor LEVEL3
        by using the ! (logical not) operator:</para>

        <programlisting>{akeebasubs !LEVEL1 &amp;&amp; !LEVEL3}Your content{/akeebasubs}</programlisting>

        <para>If you specify multiple operators, the precedence is NOT, AND,
        OR. This means that the exclamation mark is processed first, the
        ampersands second and the bars last. Example:</para>

        <programlisting>{akeebasubs !LEVEL1 || LEVEL2 &amp;&amp; !LEVEL3}Your content{/akeebasubs}</programlisting>

        <para>This means that the content will be presented to users who do
        not have a subscription to LEVEL1. Also, if they do have a LEVEL1
        subscription and they are also LEVEL2 (but not LEVEL3) subscribers the
        content will also be shown to them.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="modules">
    <title>Akeeba Subscriptions' modules</title>

    <para>Akeeba Subscriptions comes with a variety of modules to display
    customized lists of subscription levels or a list of a user's
    subscriptions. Make sure you visit your Module Manager page and have a
    look at them. You can create interesting effects, like a customized and
    categorized subscriptions list page, out of those modules.</para>

    <para>– THIS DOCUMENTATION SECTION IS UNDER CONSTRUCTION –</para>
  </chapter>
</book>
