<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Akeeba Subscriptions User's Guide</title>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Nicholas</firstname><othername>K.</othername><surname>Dionysopoulos</surname></personname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>AkeebaBackup.com</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>April 2011</pubdate>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1.0.b1</revnumber>

        <date>April 2011</date>

        <author>
          <personname><firstname>Nicholas</firstname><othername>K.</othername><surname>Dionysopoulos</surname></personname>
        </author>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
      copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled "The GNU Free
      Documentation License".</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <abstract>
      <para>This book covers the use of the Akeeba Subscriptions component and
      its bundled modules and plugins for selling and managing subscriptions
      on your <trademark>Joomla!</trademark>-powered web sites.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>

  <chapter xml:id="intro-and-installation">
    <title>Introduction and installation</title>

    <section xml:id="introduction">
      <title>Introducing Akeeba Subscriptions</title>

      <bridgehead>At a glance</bridgehead>

      <para>Akeeba Subscriptions is a subscriptions management component for
      <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> 1.5/1.6 and compatible distributions,
      such as Nooku Server and Molajo. It is built using the Nooku Framework
      and the best practices for rapid web application development which
      ensure stability and security. It is licensed under the GNU General
      Public License (GPL) version 3 or –at your option– any later version
      published by the Free Software Foundation. It licensing scheme means
      that you are free (and, in fact, more than welcome) to install it on as
      many sites as you want, whenever you want and use it for as long as you
      want, no strings attached. There are no secret per-domain licensing fees
      and you can use it to sell one or several millions of subscriptions
      without any hidden costs. We love Freedom of choice as much as you
      do!</para>

      <bridgehead>The killer features</bridgehead>

      <para>Its feature list is nothing sort of amazing, either. Out of the
      box, Akeeba Subscriptions supports these features:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Streamlined administrator interface which can even present you
          an interactive sales graph and sales report as soon as you launch
          the component</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Rich subscription levels (subscription packages) editor which
          allows you to choose different images for each of your subscriptions
          and even a different order confirmation and order cancellation text
          to show to your users.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The easiest subscription management interface you've seen on a
          component. It will even show you your users' faces, powered by
          Gravatar.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Users can upgrade or expand (renew) their subscriptions.
          Renewing a subscription will create a new subscription which becomes
          valid the very second their old one expires. Users do not lose any
          of their subscription time when renewing, unlike most other
          subscription systems out there.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Full support for delayed payments, e.g. when using e-checks
          with PayPal.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Discount coupon codes which allow you to set an absolute money
          value or percentage discount for all or a specific subscription
          level and user, have publish up/publish down dates or a usage limit
          (e.g. the coupon code is valid only for the first 100 people to use
          it) – or a combination of any and all of the above!</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Automatic discounts for upgrading or renewing subscriptions
          based on the subscription level and days of presence in the
          subscription package. This allows you to easily create rules like:
          30% discount if you renew up to 30 days before the end of your
          subscription, 15% discount if you renew within the last 30 days, no
          discount otherwise.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Full support for complex tax calculations based on country,
          state and ZIP code. It fully integrates with the European Union's
          VIES system so that you can charge no VAT tax for intra-EU B2B
          transactions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The subscription form can work with or without Javascript.
          With Javascript it becomes a fully fledged, auto-validating
          subscription form. Without Javascript it works as a standard web
          form, accessible to users who do not wish / can not use Javascript
          on their browser.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Integration with JUGA: intelligently add/remove a user from
          JUGA groups based on his active subscriptions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Content restriction: a content plugin to show parts of your
          content only to registered subscribers, without the need of any
          external tool.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Payment methods: PayPal (for personal, verified and business
          accounts) is supported out of the box</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Send emails to subscribers upon subscription, when their
          subscription/payment status changes and when their subscription is
          about to expire</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>All the attention to details that makes a component worthy of
          carrying the Akeeba label!</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <bridgehead>Support policy</bridgehead>

      <para>Please note that the software is provided free of charge, but
      support is not. You need to have an AKEEBADELUXE or SUPPORT subscription
      on AkeebaBackup.com to seek support regarding setting up, using and
      customizing Akeeba Subscriptions. If you have found a bug and wish to
      report it, however, you can do so even without an active
      AkeebaBackup.com subscription.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="requirements">
      <title>Requirements and compatibility</title>

      <para>Akeeba Subscriptions requires the following server-side
      configuration:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>PHP 5.2.6 or later. Running it on earlier versions will either
          be problematic or it won't work at all.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>MySQL 5.0 or later. Earlier database server versions will not
          be supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Your server must support the mysqli driver and your site must
          use it. If not, Akeeba Subscriptions will try to switch your site to
          mysqli upon installation.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you are using the Suhosin patch for PHP, please <link
          xlink:href="http://nooku.assembla.com/wiki/show/nooku-framework/Known_Issues">read
          this tutorial</link> to avoid any potential conflicts. Support will
          not be provided if you are affected by this Suhosin issue.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Joomla! 1.5.14 or later (fully supported) or Joomla! 1.6.0 or
          later (partial support for now). We know that some things in the
          back-end do not work properly (they look ugly or have other visual
          artifacts) with Joomla! 1.6. Fixing them would break Joomla! 1.5
          compatibility, so please don't report them as bugs – we are just not
          going to fix them yet.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The <guilabel>System - mooTools Upgrade</guilabel> system
          plugin MUST be enabled on Joomla! 1.5 sites.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Akeeba Subscriptions is compatible with other Nooku-based software
      which is using at least Nooku Framework 0.7 Alpha 2, such as Ninjaboard
      1.0.7 and later. It will not work properly together with components
      using earlier versions of the framework, such as Joomlashack's
      LifeStream. If you're in doubt, please try installing Akeeba
      Subscriptions on a copy of your site and test its behaviour.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="installation-instructions">
      <title>Installation</title>

      <section xml:id="installation">
        <title>Installation</title>

        <para>There are two available installation packages. The one with
        -noframework in its name contains only the component, modules and
        plugins of Akeeba Subscriptions. The one without -noframework contains
        everything plus a copy of the Nooku Framework. If you don't have any
        other Nooku-based software on your site, please install the regular
        package. If you have another Nooku-based software on your site, such
        as Ninjaboard 1.0.7 or later, please try installing the -noframework
        package first and, if that doesn't work properly, take a backup of
        your site and try installing the regular package.</para>

        <para>Installing the package is the same as with any other Joomla!
        component. Go to your site's back-end, Extensions, Install/Uninstall
        (Joomla! 1.5) or Extensions, Manage (Joomla! 1.6) and click on Browse.
        Locate the ZIP package and click on Upload and Install. If the
        installation fails, please refer to the installation troubleshooting
        section of this guide.</para>

        <important>
          <para>On Joomla! 1.5 sites you MUST publish the <guilabel>System -
          mooTools Upgrade</guilabel> system plugin for Akeeba Subscriptions
          to work properly. If you don't, the interface will appear broken and
          you will not be able to use the component. If you file a support
          request regarding that, we'll just reply with
          "<acronym>RTFM</acronym>" (RTFM is the acronym for Read The Fine
          Manual).</para>
        </important>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="installation-troubleshooting">
        <title>Installation troubleshooting</title>

        <bridgehead>Joomla! 1.6 is logging you out during
        installation</bridgehead>

        <para>The first thing you might observe is that <emphasis
        role="bold">Joomla! 1.6 is logging you out when trying to
        install</emphasis> Akeeba Subscriptions. This is due to a bug in
        Joomla! 1.6. Please <link
        xlink:href="http://docs.joomla.org/Why_does_the_administrator_logoff_all_of_the_sudden">follow
        these instructions</link> to fix the database table that causes this
        issue. After doing that you will have to log in again to your site.
        You will see that everything is missing from the back-end interface.
        Don't panic! That's part of the Joomla! bug. Just log out using the
        link on the top-right of your page, then log back in. Everything is
        back to normal and you can retry the installation.</para>

        <bridgehead>Joomla! 1.6 says "can't build admin menu" and
        fails</bridgehead>

        <para>On some other occasions, especially when trying to install or
        update the component after an installation error, Joomla! will
        complain that it <emphasis role="bold">can not build admin
        menus</emphasis>. This is due to another Joomla! 1.6 bug <link
        xlink:href="http://joomlacode.org/gf/project/joomla/tracker/?action=TrackerItemEdit&amp;tracker_item_id=25663">we
        have sent a patch for</link> to the Joomla! development team.
        Meanwhile, you will have to run a few SQL statements against your
        database with a database editor such as phpMyAdmin:</para>

        <programlisting>DELETE FROM jos_assets WHERE `name` = 'com_akeebasubs';
DELETE FROM jos_menu WHERE `menutype` = 'main' AND `alias` = 'com_akeebasubs';
DELETE FROM jos_extensions WHERE `type` = 'component' AND `element` = 'com_akeebasubs';</programlisting>

        <para>Remember to change <replaceable>jos_</replaceable> with your
        database tables' name prefix if you changed it during installation!
        It's easy to find out what it is. Take a look at the database and
        you'll see that all of your tables begin with the same few letters.
        That's your prefix. After running those SQL statements you can proceed
        with the reinstallation of the component.</para>

        <bridgehead>Version check</bridgehead>

        <para>Check your Joomla! version. Joomla! 1.5.0 through 1.5.10 can not
        install Akeeba Subscriptions. This is a limitation of these extremely
        outdated releases. If you have such a site, upgrade it. Joomla! 1.5.11
        through 1.5.14 may or may not be able to install Akeeba Subscriptions.
        Again, these are limitations of those outdated Joomla! releases on
        certain hosts. The only workaround is to upgrade your Joomla!
        installation.</para>

        <para>If you have Joomla! 1.6 make sure that you are using Joomla!
        1.6.0 (the "stable" release, not the RC or any of the betas). Mind
        you, we have only tested the installation with Joomla! 1.6.2 and later
        releases.</para>

        <bridgehead>Checking your temporary directory</bridgehead>

        <para>First, we will have to make sure that you are using a valid
        temporary directory. Many sites are configured to use the system-wide
        (/tmp) directory or an invalid directory, causing installation
        problems. In order to change your site's temporary directory setting
        you have to follow this procedure, depending on your Joomla!
        version.</para>

        <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Joomla! 1.5</bridgehead>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Go to your site's administrator back-end and click
            <guimenu>Help</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>System Info</guimenuitem>
            from the top menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <guilabel>Directory permissions</guilabel>
            link</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Scroll down the page and find the first <guilabel>Cache
            Directory</guilabel> line. It is the fourth from the bottom of the
            page.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Next to the <guilabel>Cache directory</guilabel> label you
            can see a path, e.g.
            <filename>/home/myuser/public_html/cache</filename></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Replace the <filename>cache</filename> word with
            <filename>tmp</filename> in that path, i.e.
            <filename>/home/myuser/public_html/tmp</filename> and note down
            this path. This is your new temp path.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Go to <guimenu>Site</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Global
            Configuration</guimenuitem> menu item from the top menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <guilabel>Server</guilabel> link</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Find the "Path to Temp-folder" and replace its contents with
            the new temp path from step #5.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Save your Global Configuration</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Joomla! 1.6</bridgehead>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Create a file named mynewtmp.php with the following
            contents:</para>

            <programlisting>&lt;?php echo dirname(__FILE__).'/tmp';</programlisting>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Upload the file to your site and access it as
            http://www.example.com/mynewtmp.php where www.example.com is the
            domain name to your site.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Write down what you see on the screen. That's your new
            temporary directory path.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Remove the mynewtmp.php file from your site.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Go to your site's administrator back-end and click on
            <guimenu>Site</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Global
            Configuration</guimenuitem> menu item from the top menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <guilabel>Server</guilabel> link</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Find the "Path to Temp-folder" and replace its contents with
            the new temp path from step #3.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Save your Global Configuration</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <bridgehead>Enable FTP</bridgehead>

        <para>On most shared hosts which do not run suPHP (if you didn't
        understand anything, most likely the following <emphasis>is applicable
        to you too</emphasis>) you have to enable Joomla!'s FTP layer.
        Otherwise Joomla! won't be able to write the files to its directories
        and installation will fail.</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Go to <guimenu>Site</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Global
            Configuration</guimenuitem> menu item from the top menu.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the <guilabel>Server</guilabel> tab</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Set <guilabel>Enable FTP</guilabel> to Yes</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the <guilabel>FTP Host</guilabel> try using
            <option>127.0.0.1</option> or <option>localhost</option> or the
            FTP hostname assigned by your host</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the <guilabel>FTP Username</guilabel> and <guilabel>FTP
            Password</guilabel> fields provide the FTP username and password
            assigned by your host</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the <guilabel>FTP Root</guilabel> you have to type in the
            FTP path to your site's root. Here is the easy way to find it
            using <link
            xlink:href="http://filezilla-project.org/download.php">FileZilla</link>:</para>

            <para>Connect to your site using FileZilla. Navigate inside the
            folder Joomla! is installed in. Usually it's a directory named
            <filename>public_html</filename>, <filename>htdocs</filename>,
            <filename>www</filename> or something similar. If unsure don't ask
            us, ask your host. Now, on the right-hand pane you will find the
            FTP path. Most likely it will look something like
            <filename>/public_html</filename>. Copy this and paste it into the
            FTP Root text box in your Joomla!'s Global Configuration
            page.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Save your Global Configuration. If you got everything
            correctly, you should see a message that your configuration was
            saved. If you see an error message please seek assistance on the
            <link xlink:href="http://forum.joomla.org">Joomla!
            Forum</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <bridgehead>Manual installation</bridgehead>

        <para>Sometimes <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> is unable to properly
        extract ZIP archives due to technical limitations on your server. In
        this case, you can follow a manual installation procedure.</para>

        <para>First, you have to extract the installation ZIP file in a
        subdirectory named <filename>akeeba</filename> on your local PC. Then,
        upload the entire subdirectory inside your site's temporary directory.
        At this point, there should be a subdirectory named
        <filename>akeeba</filename> inside your site's temporary directory
        which contains all of the ZIP package's files.</para>

        <para>If you are unsure where your site's temporary directory is
        located, you can look it up by going to the <guimenuitem>Global
        Configuration</guimenuitem>, click on the <guilabel>Server</guilabel>
        tab and take a look at the <guilabel>Path to Temp-folder</guilabel>
        setting. The default setting is the <filename>tmp</filename> directory
        under your site's root. Rarely, especially on automated installations
        using Fantastico, this might have been assigned the system-wide
        <filename>/tmp</filename> directory. In this case, please consult your
        host for instructions on how to upload files inside this directory, or
        read the instructions above about changing your
        <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> temporary directory back to the default
        location and making it writable.</para>

        <para>Assuming that you are past this uploading step, click on the
        <guimenu>Extensions</guimenu>,
        <guimenuitem>Install/Uninstall</guimenuitem> (Joomla! 1.5) or
        <guimenu>Extensions</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Manage</guimenuitem>
        (Joomla! 1.6 users) link on the top menu. In this page, locate the
        <guibutton>Install Directory</guibutton> edit box in the
        <guilabel>Install from Directory</guilabel> area. It is already filled
        in with the absolute path to your temporary directory, for example
        <filename>/var/www/joomla/tmp</filename>. Please append
        <filename>/akeeba</filename> to it. As per our example, it should look
        something like <filename>/var/www/joomla/tmp/akeeba</filename>. Then,
        click on the <guibutton>Install</guibutton> button.</para>

        <bridgehead>Still problems?</bridgehead>

        <para>If you still can't install Akeeba Subscriptions and you are
        receiving messages regarding unwritable directories, inability to move
        files or other similar file system related error messages, please do
        not ask us for support. These errors stem from your site set up and
        can best be resolved by asking for help in the <link
        xlink:href="http://forum.joomla.org">official
        <trademark>Joomla!</trademark> forums</link>. We can only support
        software we develop ourselves. Joomla!'s extension installer is
        certainly not developed by us and –believe us– we have tried to
        improve it and submitted some still pending patches to the Joomla!
        project. Therefore we regret that we have to say that, but we can't
        help you. Thank you for your understanding.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="setup-and-usage">
    <title>Initial set-up and usage</title>

    <section xml:id="how-subscriptions-work">
      <title>How subscriptions work</title>

      <para>Before you begin setting up Akeeba Subscriptions, you should be
      aware of the way subscriptions work under the hood. The most basic
      concept is the subscription level (referred to simply as Level from now
      on). This is what you are selling to your customers. Your customers buy
      a subscription to a Level. The composite piece of information containing
      the Level, payment information and expiration time is called a
      Subscription.</para>

      <para>When a user enters the subscription page, Akeeba Subscriptions
      first fetches the price associated with the Level your user wants to
      buy. It will then try to understand if there is an applicable discount.
      First, it will look into Upgrade definitions and produce a list of
      upgrade rules applicable for the user and the Level he wishes to buy. If
      there are multiple applicable upgrade rules, the one giving the maximum
      discount is elected. Next up, it takes a look at the coupon code, is
      supplied. If it is an active coupon and your user can use it to get a
      discount, the coupon's discount is calculated. In the case where there
      are two discounts, both an upgrade discount and a coupon discount, the
      highest one is elected. The level price minus the discount is called the
      Net Price.</para>

      <para>Right up, Akeeba Subscriptions will try to determine the
      applicable tax by going through all the tax rules. It will go through
      the tax rules and keep the one which is the closest match to the
      country, zip code, city and VIES registration status. If no match is
      found, Akeeba Subscriptions will select the tax rate defined in the very
      first tax rule you have defined. This is called the Tax Amount. The sum
      of the Net Price and Tax Amount is the Gross Amount and that's what the
      user will have to pay.</para>

      <para>When the user hits the Subscribe button, Akeeba Subscriptions will
      first check if this is a new or existing user. If it is a new user, it
      will create a new –but inactive– user account based on the information
      the user has supplied. A new, inactive subscription will be created for
      your user and he's redirected to the payment gateway. Exception: if you
      have an 100% or more discount (which means that the user shall pay
      nothing) he's not redirected to the payment gateway. Instead, he's
      redirected to the Subscription Confirmation page and his subscription
      becomes instantly active.</para>

      <para>Once the user finishes the payment, he's redirected to the
      Subscription Confirmation page. If he changes his mind and cancels the
      payment, he will be takes to the Subscription Cancellation page. The
      text on each page is determined by the relevant fields in the Level
      configuration.</para>

      <para>At the same time, your payment processor will send a post-back to
      your site, notifying Akeeba Subscriptions about the payment status. If
      the payment is marked as complete, the subscription is activated. Its
      start and expiration date are calculated based on the exact date and
      time that the payment post-back was received and the Level's configured
      length. If the associated user account was marked as blocked (inactive),
      it is activated. If any integrations are set up, they will run. For
      example, you may be adding users to JUGA groups upon a successful
      subscription.</para>

      <para>Based on the above, you need to configure the following –in the
      order shown– for Akeeba Subscriptions to work:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Configuration Options - well, that's just the currency you're
          selling in!</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Subscription Levels - the subscription products you are
          selling, i.e. your inventory</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Tax Rules - determine if the user has to be charged taxes over
          the subscription amount and how much that will be</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Upgrade rules - (optional) discounts based on what other
          products the user has bought and how long he's been a subscriber to
          them</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Coupons - (optional) discount codes used for promotions</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Alternatively, you can import Subscription Levels and Coupons from
      other subscription systems instead of manually defining them.</para>

      <para>The sections below will tell you how to go through each of these
      steps.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="configuration">
      <title>Configuration options</title>

      <para>Click on <guilabel>Configuration</guilabel> in the toolbar links
      area. The available options are:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Currency code</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <link xlink:href="http://www.xe.com/iso4217.php">three
            letter ISO 4217 currency code</link>. Common values are EUR
            (Euro), USD (United States Dollar), GBP (Great Britain Pound), CAD
            (Canada Dollar), AUD (Australia Dollar), JPY (Japan Yen), CNY
            (China Yuan) and MXN (Mexico, Pesos). This is used on virtually
            all of the payment processors to notify them about the currency
            you're selling your goods in. Please remember that all of your
            payment processors must support the selected currency. Some
            payment processors only accept a subset of currencies, most
            usually only one of USD, GBP and EUR.</para>

            <para>Default: EUR (Euro)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Currency Symbol</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The currency symbol to be shown to your web visitors, e.g. €
            for Euro, £ for British Pound, $ for US/Australia/Canada Dollar or
            ¥ for Japan Yen. This is free form text used to prefix the prices.
            If your currency has no special symbol you can use text to
            describe it, or leave blank to completely omit the currency symbol
            display throughout the components.</para>

            <para>Default: € (Euro symbol)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="subscription-levels">
      <title>Subscription Levels</title>

      <para>You can access this feature by clicking on <guilabel>Subscription
      Levels</guilabel> in the toolbar links area.</para>

      <para>Creating or editing a Subscription Level, you have these
      options:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Title</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>How the subscription will be presented to your users. We
            strongly suggest using all-capital letters and no spaces for
            easier administration, albeit you can really use anything you
            like.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Image</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select a picture to represent your subscription. The image
            must be located in your site's images/stories (Joomla! 1.5) or
            images (Joomla! 1.6) directory.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Subscription Length (days)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>How many days a subscription in this level lasts. Common
            values are 30 (one month), 180 (half a year) and 365 (one
            year).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Price</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The price of a subscription in this level. If you need to
            enter a decimal value, use a dot as the decimal separator. For
            example, 12.30 is valid, whereas 12,30 is INVALID and will be
            interpreted as 1230. Do NOT use a thousands separator. For example
            1000 is valid, whereas 1,000 is INVALID.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Slug</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The alias, used to construct the URL. Use only lowercase
            Latin characters without diacretics and accents, dashes and
            underscores. For example <option>uber-sub</option> is valid,
            whereas <option>über SUB</option> is INVALID.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Published</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Should it be shown to your users?</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Short Description</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A description of the subscription to show to your users.
            Keep it short (ca. 30 words or less) or it will overflow the
            boundaries of the subscription presentation areas in the
            front-end.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Message to show after successful sign-up</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The text in this area will be presented to the users after
            they successfully complete their payment. Use it to thank them for
            giving you their money and show them important information about
            their subscription, e.g. links to your support method, download
            links etc.</para>

            <warning>
              <para>Do not include any sensitive information (such as "secret"
              download links) as the content of this page can be directly
              accessed by a knowledgeable user by manipulating the URL. If you
              want to include such information, please use the Restricted
              Content plugin bundled with Akeeba Subscriptions to make sure
              that the information will only be shown to users holding a valid
              subscription.</para>
            </warning>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Message to show after sign-up cancellation</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The text in this area will be presented to the users after
            they cancel their payment (if your payment gateway supports this
            feature). This is your last attempt to changing your user's mind
            or have them give you feedback on the reasons they decided to not
            move forward with their subscription. Use it wisely and do not
            insult your users, please :)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="tax-rules">
      <title>Tax Rules</title>

      <para>You can access this feature by clicking on <guilabel>Tax
      Rules</guilabel> in the toolbar links area.</para>

      <para>Out of the box, Akeeba Subscriptions is set up to not apply any
      VAT or other tax at all. However, this is not what most users would
      like. Below we are providing the most common setups based on your
      business type. Our lawyers told us that we have to say this to you:
      Please note that we are not lawyers or tax technicians. As a result, our
      advice is based on our personal experience, may be flawed and in no way
      should be considered a legal or financial advice. Should you chose to
      use it you do so at your own risk. We strongly advise you to ask a
      qualified tax technician, lawyer or other relevant professional
      qualified by law to give you advice regarding tax laws. That said,
      here's the most common tax setups:</para>

      <bridgehead>Extra-EU businesses, e.g. US based</bridgehead>

      <para>Tax Rules determine if the user should be charged a tax amount on
      top of the regular price of the subscription level. If you do not wish
      to charge any taxes (e.g. you have already included any applicable taxes
      in your subscription price), you will still have to create a default
      rule with 0 tax charges. In order to do so, click on the New button,
      select the "- Select -" option in the Country drop-down and set the tax
      rate to 0, then click on Save. Now you have created a catch-all rule
      with 0% tax. Likewise, if you want to charge all users a flat tax rate,
      say 18%, do the same thing, but set the tax rate to your desired
      percentage, in our case 18 (note: without the % sign!) and click on
      Save.</para>

      <bridgehead>Intra-EU businesses with a VIES registered VAT number, or
      extra-EU businesses with an EU VAT number</bridgehead>

      <para>If you are a business based in the European Union with a
      VIES-registered VAT number you have to create a total of 30 rules to
      conform to the overcomplicated EU tax regulations. First, create a
      default rule with 0% tax as noted above. Then do the same thing, but set
      the <guilabel>VIES Reg</guilabel> option to Yes and the tax rate to 0%.
      Now create new tax rules for each one of these countries, <guilabel>VIES
      Reg</guilabel> set to No and tax rate set to your local VAT tax rate
      (e.g. 23% for Greece): United Kingdom, Austria, Belgium, Bulgaria,
      Cyprus, Czech Republic, Germany, Greece, Denmark, Estonia, Spain,
      Finland, France, Hungary, Ireland, Italy, Lithuania, Luxembourg, Latvia,
      Malta, Netherlands, Poland, Portugal, Romania, Sweden, Slovenia,
      Slovakia. For the country of your business (e.g. Greece for a
      Greece-based business) create on more rule with <guilabel>VIES
      Reg</guilabel> set to Yes and the tax rate set to your local VAT tax
      rate (e.g. 23% for Greece). This way, the following happens:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the customer is extra-EU he will be charged no VAT</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the customer is an intra-EU business, he will be charged no
          VAT (he's liable to VAT on his local tax authorities, not your
          country's tax authorities)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the customer is intra-EU, but not a business with a
          VIES-registered VAT number, he's paying VAT.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the customer is coming from your own country, you are
          charging him with VAT no matter what.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Do note that the same setup is required if you are an extra-EU
      business –e.g. US-based– with an EU VAT ID (it's in the format
      EU012345678). In this case, you have no EU country of residence, so you
      can skip the last tax rule mentioned above.</para>

      <bridgehead>Intra-EU businesses without a VIES-registered VAT
      number</bridgehead>

      <para>Please ask your lawyer whether it's legal for you to sell
      subscriptions to residents of a country other than yours. There is a gap
      in the EU directives regarding that case, therefore we can't provide you
      with even semi-accurate tax setup information within any stretch of
      imagination.</para>

      <bridgehead>Tax Rule options</bridgehead>

      <para>Each tax rule has the following options:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Country</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Which country this tax rule is applicable in. If empty (the
            "- Select -" pseudo-option of the country list) it applies to all
            countries.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>State</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Which state this tax rule is applicable in. Note: only US
            and Canada states and provinces can be selected. If left empty
            (the N/A option) it applies to all states.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>City</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Which city this tax rule is applicable in. Do note that the
            spelling of the city must match, but it's case insensitive. This
            means that <option>new york</option>, <option>NEW YORK</option>
            and <option>New York</option> are equivalent. Leave blank to match
            all cities.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>VIES Reg</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If set to Yes, the tax rule matches only those clients with
            a valid, VIES registered EU VAT number. If you don't know what
            VIES registration is, <link
            xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/taxation_customs/taxation/vat/traders/vat_number/index_en.htm">read
            this</link>. You can verify if a VAT number of an EU resident or
            EU registered business is also VIES registered through EU's <link
            xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/taxation_customs/vies/">official
            web application on Europa.eu</link>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Tax Rate</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The tax rate percentage. If you need to enter decimal
            digits, use a dot not a comma. For example, <option>17.5</option>
            is valid, <option>17,5</option> is INVALID. Do NOT type the
            percentage sign. For example, <option>23</option> is valid,
            <option>23%</option> is INVALID. The percentage is always implied,
            that's why it's printed after the field's contents.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Enabled</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If set to Yes, the VAT Rule will be applied, otherwise it
            will be ignored (as if it weren't set at all)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="upgrade-rules">
      <title>Upgrade Rules</title>

      <para>You can access this feature by clicking on
      <guilabel>Upgrades</guilabel> in the toolbar links area.</para>

      <para>This feature allows you to create automatically applied discount
      rules to reward your loyal customers by giving them a discount. If you
      are not sure this is what you want to do, I strongly suggest reading
      Seth Godin's "<link
      xlink:href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2011/02/how-should-you-treat-your-best-customers.html">How
      should you treat your best customers?</link>" and view <link
      xlink:href="http://www.attorneymarketing.com/2010/04/25/seth-godin-explains-how-to-build-a-tribe-of-loyal-clients/">this
      video of his</link> where he explains his ideas on small businesses even
      more clearly.</para>

      <para>Each Upgrade rule has the following options:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Title</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Just a title to remind you of what this upgrade rule
            does</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Published</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If set to No, it won't be taken into account during a new
            subscription's price calculation</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>From level</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The subscription level for which the user must already have
            a valid subscription in order for the upgrade rule to take
            effect</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>To Level</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The subscription level which the user is currently trying to
            subscribe to and onto which the discount will be applied</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Min. Presence</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The minimum number of days the user has to have a valid
            subscription to From Level for this rule to be applied</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Max. Presence</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The maximum number of days the user has to have a valid
            subscription to From Level for this rule to be applied</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Discount Type</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If it's Value, the Value field contains currency, e.g. if
            you're using Euros and type a value of 20 then 20 Euros will be
            subtracted from the price. If its Percent, then the Value field
            contains a percentage, e.g. if you type a value of 20 then a 20%
            discount will be applied to the price.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Value</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>See above.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>Practical examples of upgrade rules:</para>

      <para>You want to give a 30% discount to users with a SUB1 annual
      subscription if they renew up to 30 days before their subscription
      expiration. Both levels set to SUB1, min presence is set to 0, max
      presence is set to 335 (one year is 365 days, minus 30 days, equals 335
      days), discount type Percent, value 30.</para>

      <para>You want to give a 15% discount to users with a SUB1 annual
      subscription if they renew during the last 30 days of their
      subscription. Both levels set to SUB1, min presence is set to 335 (one
      year is 365 days, minus 30 days, equals 335 days), max presence set to
      365 (one full year) discount type Percent, value 15.</para>

      <para>You want to give a 10 Euro discount to users with a SUB1 annual
      subscription who are now buying a SUB2 subscription. From Level set to
      SUB1, To Level set to SUB2, min presence set to 0, max presence set to
      365 (one year), discount set to Value, value set to 10.</para>

      <para>You want users buying both SUB1 and SUB2 to have a 10 Euro
      discount. First, create a rule like in the previous example. Then create
      another rule with From Level set to SUB2, To Level set to SUB1, min
      presence set to 0, max presence set to 365, discount set to Value, value
      set to 10. This way, whichever subscription they buy first, they'll get
      the discount when they buy the other subscription as well.</para>

      <para>You want to give a complimentary (free) SUB3 subscription to users
      who have already bought SUB1 and SUB2: you can't do that with Upgrade
      Rules, as you can not combine multiple subscriptions in a single rule.
      Instead, use a coupon code with 100% discount and show this coupon code
      only to subscribers who have already bought a SUB1 and SUB2 subscription
      using the Restricted Content plugin bundled with Akeeba
      Subscriptions.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="coupons">
      <title>Coupons</title>

      <para>You can access this feature by clicking on
      <guilabel>Coupons</guilabel> in the toolbar links area.</para>

      <para>This feature allows you to create discount coupon codes. When a
      user enters a valid coupon code during registration, it's subtracted
      from the price of his subscription. You can let coupons work on specific
      subscriptions, specific users, for a predefined time period or even for
      a predefined number of times before becoming inactive. You can even
      create 100% discount coupons for giveaways or other similar promotional
      reasons.</para>

      <para>Each coupon supports the following fields:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Title</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A descriptive title for your coupon. It is only displayed to
            you, it is not displayed to your users.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Coupon code</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The coupon code which the user has to enter in order to
            receive the discount. Very important: coupon codes are case
            insensitive, therefore it's best to type them in all capital
            letters. Moreover, we suggest using only capital Latin letters
            without accents or diacretics and numbers, so that all users can
            type them in using their keyboard.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Discount type</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>You can either specify Percent (give an X% discount over the
            price) or Value (deducts X from the price). It works in
            conjunction with the Value field below. For example, if you are
            using Euros as your currency, you set Value here and type in a
            value of 10, the coupon gives 10 Euro discount.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Discount value</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>See above</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Published</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Set to Yes for the coupon to become active</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Hits</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This is the number of times this coupon has been
            used.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Valid from</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>When the coupon will become active (note: the date is
            expressed in the GMT/UTC timezone). Leave blank or set to
            0000-00-00 00:00:00 to make the coupon active right now. Note: a
            published coupon will not be taken into account before its Valid
            From date.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Valid to</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>When the coupon will become inactive (note: the date is
            expressed in the GMT/UTC timezone). Leave blank or set to
            0000-00-00 00:00:00 to let Akeeba Subscriptions ignore this field
            and let the coupon active until you manually unpublish it. Note: a
            published coupon will not be taken into account after its Valid To
            date.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Limit to a specific user</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click on <guibutton>Select</guibutton> to pick a user for
            which the coupon will be active. For all other users the coupon
            will have no effect. Leave blank to let all users –even new ones–
            to use the coupon.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Subscription Levels</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Choose the subscription levels which the coupon code can be
            applied to. Leave it blank (or make sure that only the <option>-
            Select -</option> pseudo-option is selected) to let Akeeba
            Subscriptions apply the coupon to all current and future
            subscription levels you are offering on your site.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Hits limit</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If it is greater than zero, the coupon can be used up to
            this number of times before it becomes inactive. In other words,
            when the Hits counter becomes equal to Hits Limit, the coupon can
            no longer be used by anyone. Leave it blank to not apply any such
            limit.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="subscriptions-management">
      <title>Subscriptions management</title>

      <para>You can access this feature by clicking on
      <guilabel>Subscriptions</guilabel> in the toolbar links area.</para>

      <para>This is a standard Joomla! administrator page which needs no
      explanation.</para>

      <para>The icons on the left hand side of the user information are
      Gravatars. If the user has linked a Gravatar to their email address, it
      is displayed next to their name, otherwise a default avatar (head-shaped
      cut out) is displayed.</para>

      <para>In order to edit a subscription, click on the leftmost column (the
      numeric ID) of the subscription record. Clicking on the other links will
      edit the respective item, i.e. clicking on the subscription level will
      open the subscription level editor.</para>

      <para>You can use the <guibutton>Run Integrations</guibutton> button any
      time in order to have Akeeba Subscriptions re-process all integrations
      with third party components. This is useful when you suspect an
      integration has gone wrong, you changed the options in an integration
      plugin or you just imported a large number of subscriptions.</para>

      <para>Using the CSV button allows you to export the current view into a
      CSV file for further processing in a spreadsheet application such as
      Microsoft Office Excel, Apple Numbers or OpenOffice.org Calc. Do note
      that the full set of raw data is dumped to the CSV file.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="frotn-end-items">
      <title>Front-end items</title>

      <para>There are four types of front-end menu items you can
      create:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Subscribe • Specific Level</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Allows you to create a menu link to the subscription page of
            a specific Subscription Level</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Subscription Levels • Awesome Layout</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Presents a list of all available subscription levels in a
            comparison table, using CSS3 styling. It's the most eye-catching
            presentation layout and it's best to use only if you have a small
            number of subscription levels (4 to 5)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Subscription Levels • All Levels</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Presents a list of all available subscription levels as a
            two column list of boxes. It is a relatively dull presentation
            mode, but is suitable for a very large number of subscription
            levels (over 6)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>My subscriptions • All of my subscriptions</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Think of it as a kind of "My Account" page. It shows the
            user all of his subscriptions and allows him to review the
            information on each one of them, as well as renew them.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>The subscription page defines two module positions where you can
      publish modules to further expand the information presented on the page.
      Publishing modules in the <option>akeebasubscriptionsheader</option>
      position will make them appear at the very top of the page, right above
      the Steps bar. That's a good place to publish information about SSL
      security or banners about your latest special offers. Publishing modules
      in the <option>akeebasubscriptionsfooter</option> position will make
      them appear right after the end of the subscription form. This is a good
      place to put a custom HTML module with links to your terms of service,
      business contact information, etc.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="importing-from-other-components">
      <title>Importing from other components</title>

      <para>Most likely you are already using a subscriptions system and
      wouldn't like to have to manually import all of your subscriptions to
      Akeeba Subscriptions. That's why we are offering an automated import
      feature. You can access it from Akeeba Subscription's dashboard page, by
      clicking on the Operations tab, and then on
      <guibutton>Import</guibutton>.</para>

      <para>The options are:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>AMBRA.Subscriptions</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Imports subscription levels and subscriptions from
            Dioscouri's AMBRA Subscriptions (a.k.a. AMBRA.subs)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>AMBRA.Subscriptions with PayPal with VAT plugin</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you are using AMBRA.subs with my modified "PayPal with
            VAT" payment plugin and the customizations for integrating coupons
            into AMBRA.subs, you can click on this option. It will import
            subscription levels, subscriptions and any coupon codes defined.
            Moreover, it will also import the extra data stored per user, e.g.
            their address and VAT number.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <warning>
        <para>Importing from other components will DELETE AND REPLACE ANY AND
        ALL EXISTING DATA IN AKEEBA SUBSCRIPTIONS. There is NO TURNING BACK.
        Do NOT use this option after you have been using Akeeba Subscriptions
        and have new subscribers on your site.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>Please remember to review your Subscription Levels after import.
      Most notably, the text of the subscription completion and subscription
      cancellation pages will be missing from all subscription levels.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="plugins">
    <title>Payment methods, integrations and plugins</title>

    <para>Akeeba Subscriptions is designed to be a modular system, powered by
    standard Joomla! plugins. Using plugins you can add payment methods as
    well as integration with third party software. Moreover, core
    functionality of Akeeba Subscriptions (like sending out emails upon
    subscription or email reminders for subscription expiration) is take care
    of by plugins. This documentation chapter will guide you through the
    details of each plugin.</para>

    <section xml:id="payment-plugins">
      <title>Payment methods</title>

      <para>All payment methods are standard Joomla! plugins, belonging to the
      <option>akpayment</option> group. If you want to enable a payment
      method, just publish the relevant plugin.</para>

      <section xml:id="payment-paypal">
        <title>Paypal</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions Payment - Paypal</guilabel></para>

        <para>This payment method integrates the standard PayPal Website
        Payments service, available without any setup fee to all verified
        PayPal clients. In other words, that's the standard way to use PayPal
        as your payment processor. The options you have in this plugin
        are:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Payment option title</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Leave blank to use "PayPal" or type in a custom name to
              show to your customer's, e.g. "PayPal, bank account or Credit
              Card"</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Merchant ID</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Your PayPal email address or your secure merchant ID (if
              PayPal has assigned you with one)</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Secure POST</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>If enabled, the verification postback to PayPal will be
              over an SSL connection. In order for this to work, your host
              needs to support SSL connections using cURL to PayPal's IP
              address block.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Sandbox</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>When enabled, transactions are processed by PayPal
              Sandbox, i.e. PayPal's testing mode. This is designed for
              integration tests, BEFORE going live with your site. <emphasis
              role="bold">NEVER, EVER, NO MATTER WHAT YOU DO, SHOULD YOU NOT
              ENABLE THIS ON PRODUCTION SITES! IF YOU DO, YOU WILL LOSE MONEY
              AND/OR CUSTOMERS.</emphasis></para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Sandbox merchant</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The dummy merchant email used with PayPal's
              Sandbox.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>PayPal Callback Text</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>(optional) Normally, when the user completes the payment,
              PayPal shows him a button with the default label "Return to
              Merchant". If you type in something in here, it will be shown on
              that button instead of the default label. For example, you can
              type in something like "Return to Example.com"</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Custom Header Image</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>(optional) The URL to an image to be shown on PayPal's
              checkout page header. It'd better be hosted on an HTTPS URL,
              otherwise your customers will get a warning about insecure
              content on their browser.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Header Background Color</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The hex code of PayPal checkout page's header background
              color. For example, white is FFFFFF (note: there is no # sign in
              front of the hex color code!)</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Header Border Color</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The hex code of PayPal checkout page's header border
              color. For example, light gray is CCCCCC (note: there is no #
              sign in front of the hex color code!)</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="payment-none">
        <title>None</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions Payment - None</guilabel></para>

        <para>This is a dummy payment plugin which immediately activates a
        subscription without payment.</para>

        <warning>
          <para>DO NOT USE THIS ON PRODUCTION SITES. IT IS MEANT FOR TESTING
          PURPOSES ONLY. ENABLING IT ON A PRODUCTION SITE ALLOWS ANYONE,
          INCLUDING UNREGISTERED USERS, TO SUBSCRIBE TO ANY SUBSCRIPTION THEY
          WANT <emphasis role="bold">WITHOUT PAYING ANYTHING AT
          ALL</emphasis>. You have been strongly warned.</para>
        </warning>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="plugins-integration">
      <title>Integration with third party software</title>

      <para>One of the most important aspects about subscription systems is
      their ability to integrate with third party software. A subscription all
      by itself means pretty much nothing. It's just a "flag". The added value
      is when this subscription allows the user holding it to actually do
      something on the site. At this point in time, there are only a handful
      of integrations. If you are interested in more integrations let us know
      and we'll add them to our implementation to-do list.</para>

      <para>All integrations with third party applications are standard
      Joomla! plugins, published in the <option>akeebasubs</option>
      group.</para>

      <section xml:id="integration-juga">
        <title>JUGA Integration</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions - JUGA Integration</guilabel></para>

        <para>This integration plugin allows you to add and remove users from
        JUGA groups based on their subscription status. Please note that this
        is a smart integration; instead of adding users when a subscription
        goes active and removing them when a subscription goes inactive,
        Akeeba Subscriptions plugins take a look at all of the user's active
        and inactive subscriptions and decide which groups the user should be
        added to or removed from. The idea is this:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>All groups to be added to, based on active subscriptions of
            the user, are assembled to the ADD list.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>All groups to be removed from, based on inactive
            subscriptions of the user, are assembled to the REMOVE
            list.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If a JUGA group appears in both the ADD and REMOVE list, it
            is deleted from the REMOVE list. In other words "add" trumps
            "delete". In order to understand this further, here's the deal. If
            one subscription with access to a JUGA group expires, but another
            subscription granting access to the very same group is still
            active, the user's access to this group must remain active.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>The plugin has these options:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Add to JUGA groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This is a list for assigning subscription levels to JUGA
              groups. When a user has an active subscription to the specified
              level, he'll be added to the JUA group mentioned on the right
              hand of the equal sign. Each assignment is done like
              this:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3</programlisting>

              <para>Where LEVEL1 is the Title of the subscription level and
              Group 1, Group 2 and Group 3 are the names of the JUGA groups
              you want to add a user to when he subscribes. If you want to
              assign multiple subscription levels to multiple groups, you have
              to do something like that (separate multiple lines with a single
              press of the ENTER key on your keyboard):</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2,Group 3
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 4,Group 1</programlisting>

              <para>You can also use the numeric IDs of subscription levels or
              JUGA groups instead of their titles. However, we consider
              working with numeric IDs very counter-intuitive.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Remove from JUGA groups</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Likewise, this is the list of the JUGA groups to remove a
              user from when his subscription to the specified level is no
              longer active. Do note that you can specify a different set of
              groups to remove the user from than the ones you are adding him
              to. For example:</para>

              <programlisting>LEVEL1=Group 1,Group 2
LEVEL2=Group 2
LEVEL3=Group 1</programlisting>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>In this example, together with the rules displayed in "Add to
        JUGA groups", when a subscription to the LEVEL1 level expires, the
        user will still belong to JUGA's Group 3, as it's not removed from his
        account; only Group 1 and Group 2 are removed. Likewise, if the user
        has an expired LEVEL1 subscription and an active LEVEL2 subscription
        he'll now belong to Group 2 and Group 3: Group 3 because it's not
        removed when his subscription expires and Group 2 because his active
        LEVEL2 subscription suggests that he should be granted Group 2 access
        despite his expired LEVEL1 subscription.</para>

        <para>If you find this hard to understand, join the club. ACLs are not
        meant to be easy to setup or understand. It's a power feature and, as
        such, poses a great difficulty to even the most seasoned web site
        integrators. Take your time and experiment on a dev copy of your site
        before going live.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="plugins-other">
      <title>Other plugins</title>

      <para>Akeeba Subscriptions comes with more standard Joomla! plugins
      which accomplish a variety of tasks, from email communications to
      content filtering.</para>

      <section xml:id="plugin-asexpirationcontrol">
        <title>Subscription expiration control</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <emphasis
        role="bold">System - Akeeba Subscriptions Expiration
        Control</emphasis></para>

        <para>Akeeba Subscriptions will automatically expire your users'
        subscriptions when they visit a page with an Akeeba Subscriptions
        module on your site after their subscription expiration date. However,
        if you want subscription expiration to be performed automatically, you
        need to publish this plugin. It will fire once per day, expiring
        subscriptions past their expiration date. We strongly recommend
        publishing this plugin at all times.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="plugin-subscriptionemails">
        <title>Subscription emails</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Akeeba
        Subscriptions - Emails</guilabel></para>

        <para>When this plugin is published, an email will be sent out to the
        user when any of these events takes place:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A new subscription is created</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The payment status changes, e.g. the user completes the
            payment, or a delayed payment is marked as completed or
            cancelled.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A subscription expires and becomes inactive</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <note>
          <para>This plugin uses Joomla!'s mail system. You have to ensure
          that your site can send out emails (e.g. use the Mass Mail feature
          to send a test email to Super Administrators) before activating this
          plugin.</para>
        </note>

        <para>We strongly recommend publishing this plugin at all
        times.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="plugin-asexpirationnotify">
        <title>Subscription expiration notification</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>System - Akeeba
        Subscriptions Expiration Notification</guilabel></para>

        <para>This plugin will notify a user 30 and 15 days before his
        subscription's expiration. These time limits are non-configurable in
        this release.</para>

        <note>
          <para>This plugin uses Joomla!'s mail system. You have to ensure
          that your site can send out emails (e.g. use the Mass Mail feature
          to send a test email to Super Administrators) before activating this
          plugin.</para>
        </note>

        <para>We strongly recommend publishing this plugin at all
        times.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="plugin-asrestricted">
        <title>Content restriction</title>

        <para>Displayed in the Plugins Manager as: <guilabel>Content - Akeeba
        Subscriptions Restricted</guilabel></para>

        <para>This content plugin allows you to show parts of your content
        only to specific subscribers. This is a very powerful feature that
        allows you to alter the displayed content based on the user's
        subscription status.</para>

        <note>
          <para>It can not "hide" entire articles, e.g. not show them at all
          to non-subscribers. At best, only the title will be shown. If you
          want to completely hide articles and block unsubscribed user access
          to entire categories or sections you will have to use an ACL
          solution, like Dioscouri's JUGA, NoixACL or similar.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Its syntax is:</para>

        <programlisting>{akeebasubs <replaceable>expression</replaceable>}Your content{/akeebasubs}</programlisting>

        <para>This means that "Your content" will only be displayed to users
        whose subscriptions satisfy the <replaceable>expression</replaceable>.
        In the simplest form, expression is just the name of a subscription
        level, e.g.</para>

        <programlisting>{akeebasubs LEVEL1}Your content{/akeebasubs}</programlisting>

        <para>If you want to present the content to someone who holds an
        active subscription to both LEVEL1 and LEVEL2, you can use the
        <option>&amp;&amp;</option> (logic and) operator:</para>

        <programlisting>{akeebasubs LEVEL1 <option>&amp;&amp;</option> LEVEL2}Your content{/akeebasubs}</programlisting>

        <para>Likewise, you can use the || (logic or) operator to present the
        content to anyone who has a subscription to any of LEVEL3 or LEVEL4
        levels:</para>

        <programlisting>{akeebasubs LEVEL3 <option>||</option> LEVEL4}Your content{/akeebasubs}</programlisting>

        <para>Important note: The logical OR consists of two "pipe" symbols.
        These are not the same as capital I! On a Mac's keyboard, the pipe
        symbol is present next to the ENTER key, accessible by pressing
        SHIFT-\. On most Windows/Linux machines, this key is usually somewhere
        near the ENTER key and is most likely accessible by pressing SHIFT-\
        as well.</para>

        <para>You can also negate the logic. For example, you can present the
        content to anyone having a subscription to neither LEVEL1 nor LEVEL3
        by using the ! (logical not) operator:</para>

        <programlisting>{akeebasubs !LEVEL1 &amp;&amp; !LEVEL3}Your content{/akeebasubs}</programlisting>

        <para>If you specify multiple operators, the precedence is NOT, AND,
        OR. This means that the exclamation mark is processed first, the
        ampersands second and the bars last. Example:</para>

        <programlisting>{akeebasubs !LEVEL1 || LEVEL2 &amp;&amp; !LEVEL3}Your content{/akeebasubs}</programlisting>

        <para>This means that the content will be presented to users who do
        not have a subscription to LEVEL1. Also, if they do have a LEVEL1
        subscription and they are also LEVEL2 (but not LEVEL3) subscribers the
        content will also be shown to them.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="modules">
    <title>Akeeba Subscriptions' modules</title>

    <para>Akeeba Subscriptions comes with a variety of modules to display
    customized lists of subscription levels or a list of a user's
    subscriptions. Make sure you visit your Module Manager page and have a
    look at them. You can create interesting effects, like a customized and
    categorized subscriptions list page, out of those modules.</para>

    <para>– THIS DOCUMENTATION SECTION IS UNDER CONSTRUCTION –</para>
  </chapter>

  <appendix xml:id="gpl">
    <title><acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License version 3</title>

    <para>Version 3, 29 June 2007</para>

    <para>Copyright © 2007 Free Software Foundation, Inc. <link
    xlink:href="http://fsf.org/">http://fsf.org/</link></para>

    <para>Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies of this
    license document, but changing it is not allowed.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="Preamble">Preamble</bridgehead>

    <para>The <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License is a free,
    copyleft license for software and other kinds of works.</para>

    <para>The licenses for most software and other practical works are
    designed to take away your freedom to share and change the works. By
    contrast, the <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License is intended to
    guarantee your freedom to share and change all versions of a program—to
    make sure it remains free software for all its users. We, the Free
    Software Foundation, use the <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License
    for most of our software; it applies also to any other work released this
    way by its authors. You can apply it to your programs, too.</para>

    <para>When we speak of free software, we are referring to freedom, not
    price. Our General Public Licenses are designed to make sure that you have
    the freedom to distribute copies of free software (and charge for them if
    you wish), that you receive source code or can get it if you want it, that
    you can change the software or use pieces of it in new free programs, and
    that you know you can do these things.</para>

    <para>To protect your rights, we need to prevent others from denying you
    these rights or asking you to surrender the rights. Therefore, you have
    certain responsibilities if you distribute copies of the software, or if
    you modify it: responsibilities to respect the freedom of others.</para>

    <para>For example, if you distribute copies of such a program, whether
    gratis or for a fee, you must pass on to the recipients the same freedoms
    that you received. You must make sure that they, too, receive or can get
    the source code. And you must show them these terms so they know their
    rights.</para>

    <para>Developers that use the <acronym>GNU</acronym>
    <acronym>GPL</acronym> protect your rights with two steps: (1) assert
    copyright on the software, and (2) offer you this License giving you legal
    permission to copy, distribute and/or modify it.</para>

    <para>For the developers' and authors' protection, the
    <acronym>GPL</acronym> clearly explains that there is no warranty for this
    free software. For both users' and authors' sake, the
    <acronym>GPL</acronym> requires that modified versions be marked as
    changed, so that their problems will not be attributed erroneously to
    authors of previous versions.</para>

    <para>Some devices are designed to deny users access to install or run
    modified versions of the software inside them, although the manufacturer
    can do so. This is fundamentally incompatible with the aim of protecting
    users' freedom to change the software. The systematic pattern of such
    abuse occurs in the area of products for individuals to use, which is
    precisely where it is most unacceptable. Therefore, we have designed this
    version of the <acronym>GPL</acronym> to prohibit the practice for those
    products. If such problems arise substantially in other domains, we stand
    ready to extend this provision to those domains in future versions of the
    <acronym>GPL</acronym>, as needed to protect the freedom of users.</para>

    <para>Finally, every program is threatened constantly by software patents.
    States should not allow patents to restrict development and use of
    software on general-purpose computers, but in those that do, we wish to
    avoid the special danger that patents applied to a free program could make
    it effectively proprietary. To prevent this, the <acronym>GPL</acronym>
    assures that patents cannot be used to render the program non-free.</para>

    <para>The precise terms and conditions for copying, distribution and
    modification follow.</para>

    <bridgehead>TERMS AND CONDITIONS</bridgehead>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="Definitions">0.
    Definitions.</bridgehead>

    <para>“This License” refers to version 3 of the <acronym>GNU</acronym>
    General Public License.</para>

    <para>“Copyright” also means copyright-like laws that apply to other kinds
    of works, such as semiconductor masks.</para>

    <para>“The Program” refers to any copyrightable work licensed under this
    License. Each licensee is addressed as “you”. “Licensees” and “recipients”
    may be individuals or organizations.</para>

    <para>To “modify” a work means to copy from or adapt all or part of the
    work in a fashion requiring copyright permission, other than the making of
    an exact copy. The resulting work is called a “modified version” of the
    earlier work or a work “based on” the earlier work.</para>

    <para>A “covered work” means either the unmodified Program or a work based
    on the Program.</para>

    <para>To “propagate” a work means to do anything with it that, without
    permission, would make you directly or secondarily liable for infringement
    under applicable copyright law, except executing it on a computer or
    modifying a private copy. Propagation includes copying, distribution (with
    or without modification), making available to the public, and in some
    countries other activities as well.</para>

    <para>To “convey” a work means any kind of propagation that enables other
    parties to make or receive copies. Mere interaction with a user through a
    computer network, with no transfer of a copy, is not conveying.</para>

    <para>An interactive user interface displays “Appropriate Legal Notices”
    to the extent that it includes a convenient and prominently visible
    feature that (1) displays an appropriate copyright notice, and (2) tells
    the user that there is no warranty for the work (except to the extent that
    warranties are provided), that licensees may convey the work under this
    License, and how to view a copy of this License. If the interface presents
    a list of user commands or options, such as a menu, a prominent item in
    the list meets this criterion.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="SourceCode">1. Source
    Code.</bridgehead>

    <para>The “source code” for a work means the preferred form of the work
    for making modifications to it. “Object code” means any non-source form of
    a work.</para>

    <para>A “Standard Interface” means an interface that either is an official
    standard defined by a recognized standards body, or, in the case of
    interfaces specified for a particular programming language, one that is
    widely used among developers working in that language.</para>

    <para>The “System Libraries” of an executable work include anything, other
    than the work as a whole, that (a) is included in the normal form of
    packaging a Major Component, but which is not part of that Major
    Component, and (b) serves only to enable use of the work with that Major
    Component, or to implement a Standard Interface for which an
    implementation is available to the public in source code form. A “Major
    Component”, in this context, means a major essential component (kernel,
    window system, and so on) of the specific operating system (if any) on
    which the executable work runs, or a compiler used to produce the work, or
    an object code interpreter used to run it.</para>

    <para>The “Corresponding Source” for a work in object code form means all
    the source code needed to generate, install, and (for an executable work)
    run the object code and to modify the work, including scripts to control
    those activities. However, it does not include the work's System
    Libraries, or general-purpose tools or generally available free programs
    which are used unmodified in performing those activities but which are not
    part of the work. For example, Corresponding Source includes interface
    definition files associated with source files for the work, and the source
    code for shared libraries and dynamically linked subprograms that the work
    is specifically designed to require, such as by intimate data
    communication or control flow between those subprograms and other parts of
    the work.</para>

    <para>The Corresponding Source need not include anything that users can
    regenerate automatically from other parts of the Corresponding
    Source.</para>

    <para>The Corresponding Source for a work in source code form is that same
    work.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="BasicPermissions">2. Basic
    Permissions.</bridgehead>

    <para>All rights granted under this License are granted for the term of
    copyright on the Program, and are irrevocable provided the stated
    conditions are met. This License explicitly affirms your unlimited
    permission to run the unmodified Program. The output from running a
    covered work is covered by this License only if the output, given its
    content, constitutes a covered work. This License acknowledges your rights
    of fair use or other equivalent, as provided by copyright law.</para>

    <para>You may make, run and propagate covered works that you do not
    convey, without conditions so long as your license otherwise remains in
    force. You may convey covered works to others for the sole purpose of
    having them make modifications exclusively for you, or provide you with
    facilities for running those works, provided that you comply with the
    terms of this License in conveying all material for which you do not
    control copyright. Those thus making or running the covered works for you
    must do so exclusively on your behalf, under your direction and control,
    on terms that prohibit them from making any copies of your copyrighted
    material outside their relationship with you.</para>

    <para>Conveying under any other circumstances is permitted solely under
    the conditions stated below. Sublicensing is not allowed; section 10 makes
    it unnecessary.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="Protecting">3. Protecting Users'
    Legal Rights From Anti-Circumvention Law.</bridgehead>

    <para>No covered work shall be deemed part of an effective technological
    measure under any applicable law fulfilling obligations under article 11
    of the WIPO copyright treaty adopted on 20 December 1996, or similar laws
    prohibiting or restricting circumvention of such measures.</para>

    <para>When you convey a covered work, you waive any legal power to forbid
    circumvention of technological measures to the extent such circumvention
    is effected by exercising rights under this License with respect to the
    covered work, and you disclaim any intention to limit operation or
    modification of the work as a means of enforcing, against the work's
    users, your or third parties' legal rights to forbid circumvention of
    technological measures.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="ConveyingVerbatim">4. Conveying
    Verbatim Copies.</bridgehead>

    <para>You may convey verbatim copies of the Program's source code as you
    receive it, in any medium, provided that you conspicuously and
    appropriately publish on each copy an appropriate copyright notice; keep
    intact all notices stating that this License and any non-permissive terms
    added in accord with section 7 apply to the code; keep intact all notices
    of the absence of any warranty; and give all recipients a copy of this
    License along with the Program.</para>

    <para>You may charge any price or no price for each copy that you convey,
    and you may offer support or warranty protection for a fee.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="ConveyingModified">5. Conveying
    Modified Source Versions.</bridgehead>

    <para>You may convey a work based on the Program, or the modifications to
    produce it from the Program, in the form of source code under the terms of
    section 4, provided that you also meet all of these conditions:</para>

    <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
      <listitem>
        <para>The work must carry prominent notices stating that you modified
        it, and giving a relevant date.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The work must carry prominent notices stating that it is
        released under this License and any conditions added under section 7.
        This requirement modifies the requirement in section 4 to “keep intact
        all notices”.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You must license the entire work, as a whole, under this License
        to anyone who comes into possession of a copy. This License will
        therefore apply, along with any applicable section 7 additional terms,
        to the whole of the work, and all its parts, regardless of how they
        are packaged. This License gives no permission to license the work in
        any other way, but it does not invalidate such permission if you have
        separately received it.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If the work has interactive user interfaces, each must display
        Appropriate Legal Notices; however, if the Program has interactive
        interfaces that do not display Appropriate Legal Notices, your work
        need not make them do so.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>A compilation of a covered work with other separate and independent
    works, which are not by their nature extensions of the covered work, and
    which are not combined with it such as to form a larger program, in or on
    a volume of a storage or distribution medium, is called an “aggregate” if
    the compilation and its resulting copyright are not used to limit the
    access or legal rights of the compilation's users beyond what the
    individual works permit. Inclusion of a covered work in an aggregate does
    not cause this License to apply to the other parts of the
    aggregate.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="ConveyingNonSource">6. Conveying
    Non-Source Forms.</bridgehead>

    <para>You may convey a covered work in object code form under the terms of
    sections 4 and 5, provided that you also convey the machine-readable
    Corresponding Source under the terms of this License, in one of these
    ways:</para>

    <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
      <listitem>
        <para>Convey the object code in, or embodied in, a physical product
        (including a physical distribution medium), accompanied by the
        Corresponding Source fixed on a durable physical medium customarily
        used for software interchange.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Convey the object code in, or embodied in, a physical product
        (including a physical distribution medium), accompanied by a written
        offer, valid for at least three years and valid for as long as you
        offer spare parts or customer support for that product model, to give
        anyone who possesses the object code either (1) a copy of the
        Corresponding Source for all the software in the product that is
        covered by this License, on a durable physical medium customarily used
        for software interchange, for a price no more than your reasonable
        cost of physically performing this conveying of source, or (2) access
        to copy the Corresponding Source from a network server at no
        charge.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Convey individual copies of the object code with a copy of the
        written offer to provide the Corresponding Source. This alternative is
        allowed only occasionally and noncommercially, and only if you
        received the object code with such an offer, in accord with subsection
        6b.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Convey the object code by offering access from a designated
        place (gratis or for a charge), and offer equivalent access to the
        Corresponding Source in the same way through the same place at no
        further charge. You need not require recipients to copy the
        Corresponding Source along with the object code. If the place to copy
        the object code is a network server, the Corresponding Source may be
        on a different server (operated by you or a third party) that supports
        equivalent copying facilities, provided you maintain clear directions
        next to the object code saying where to find the Corresponding Source.
        Regardless of what server hosts the Corresponding Source, you remain
        obligated to ensure that it is available for as long as needed to
        satisfy these requirements.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Convey the object code using peer-to-peer transmission, provided
        you inform other peers where the object code and Corresponding Source
        of the work are being offered to the general public at no charge under
        subsection 6d.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>A separable portion of the object code, whose source code is
    excluded from the Corresponding Source as a System Library, need not be
    included in conveying the object code work.</para>

    <para>A “User Product” is either (1) a “consumer product”, which means any
    tangible personal property which is normally used for personal, family, or
    household purposes, or (2) anything designed or sold for incorporation
    into a dwelling. In determining whether a product is a consumer product,
    doubtful cases shall be resolved in favor of coverage. For a particular
    product received by a particular user, “normally used” refers to a typical
    or common use of that class of product, regardless of the status of the
    particular user or of the way in which the particular user actually uses,
    or expects or is expected to use, the product. A product is a consumer
    product regardless of whether the product has substantial commercial,
    industrial or non-consumer uses, unless such uses represent the only
    significant mode of use of the product.</para>

    <para>“Installation Information” for a User Product means any methods,
    procedures, authorization keys, or other information required to install
    and execute modified versions of a covered work in that User Product from
    a modified version of its Corresponding Source. The information must
    suffice to ensure that the continued functioning of the modified object
    code is in no case prevented or interfered with solely because
    modification has been made.</para>

    <para>If you convey an object code work under this section in, or with, or
    specifically for use in, a User Product, and the conveying occurs as part
    of a transaction in which the right of possession and use of the User
    Product is transferred to the recipient in perpetuity or for a fixed term
    (regardless of how the transaction is characterized), the Corresponding
    Source conveyed under this section must be accompanied by the Installation
    Information. But this requirement does not apply if neither you nor any
    third party retains the ability to install modified object code on the
    User Product (for example, the work has been installed in
    <acronym>ROM</acronym>).</para>

    <para>The requirement to provide Installation Information does not include
    a requirement to continue to provide support service, warranty, or updates
    for a work that has been modified or installed by the recipient, or for
    the User Product in which it has been modified or installed. Access to a
    network may be denied when the modification itself materially and
    adversely affects the operation of the network or violates the rules and
    protocols for communication across the network.</para>

    <para>Corresponding Source conveyed, and Installation Information
    provided, in accord with this section must be in a format that is publicly
    documented (and with an implementation available to the public in source
    code form), and must require no special password or key for unpacking,
    reading or copying.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="AdditionalTerms">7. Additional
    Terms.</bridgehead>

    <para>“Additional permissions” are terms that supplement the terms of this
    License by making exceptions from one or more of its conditions.
    Additional permissions that are applicable to the entire Program shall be
    treated as though they were included in this License, to the extent that
    they are valid under applicable law. If additional permissions apply only
    to part of the Program, that part may be used separately under those
    permissions, but the entire Program remains governed by this License
    without regard to the additional permissions.</para>

    <para>When you convey a copy of a covered work, you may at your option
    remove any additional permissions from that copy, or from any part of it.
    (Additional permissions may be written to require their own removal in
    certain cases when you modify the work.) You may place additional
    permissions on material, added by you to a covered work, for which you
    have or can give appropriate copyright permission.</para>

    <para>Notwithstanding any other provision of this License, for material
    you add to a covered work, you may (if authorized by the copyright holders
    of that material) supplement the terms of this License with terms:</para>

    <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
      <listitem>
        <para>Disclaiming warranty or limiting liability differently from the
        terms of sections 15 and 16 of this License; or</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Requiring preservation of specified reasonable legal notices or
        author attributions in that material or in the Appropriate Legal
        Notices displayed by works containing it; or</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Prohibiting misrepresentation of the origin of that material, or
        requiring that modified versions of such material be marked in
        reasonable ways as different from the original version; or</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Limiting the use for publicity purposes of names of licensors or
        authors of the material; or</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Declining to grant rights under trademark law for use of some
        trade names, trademarks, or service marks; or</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Requiring indemnification of licensors and authors of that
        material by anyone who conveys the material (or modified versions of
        it) with contractual assumptions of liability to the recipient, for
        any liability that these contractual assumptions directly impose on
        those licensors and authors.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>All other non-permissive additional terms are considered “further
    restrictions” within the meaning of section 10. If the Program as you
    received it, or any part of it, contains a notice stating that it is
    governed by this License along with a term that is a further restriction,
    you may remove that term. If a license document contains a further
    restriction but permits relicensing or conveying under this License, you
    may add to a covered work material governed by the terms of that license
    document, provided that the further restriction does not survive such
    relicensing or conveying.</para>

    <para>If you add terms to a covered work in accord with this section, you
    must place, in the relevant source files, a statement of the additional
    terms that apply to those files, or a notice indicating where to find the
    applicable terms.</para>

    <para>Additional terms, permissive or non-permissive, may be stated in the
    form of a separately written license, or stated as exceptions; the above
    requirements apply either way.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="Termination">8.
    Termination.</bridgehead>

    <para>You may not propagate or modify a covered work except as expressly
    provided under this License. Any attempt otherwise to propagate or modify
    it is void, and will automatically terminate your rights under this
    License (including any patent licenses granted under the third paragraph
    of section 11).</para>

    <para>However, if you cease all violation of this License, then your
    license from a particular copyright holder is reinstated (a)
    provisionally, unless and until the copyright holder explicitly and
    finally terminates your license, and (b) permanently, if the copyright
    holder fails to notify you of the violation by some reasonable means prior
    to 60 days after the cessation.</para>

    <para>Moreover, your license from a particular copyright holder is
    reinstated permanently if the copyright holder notifies you of the
    violation by some reasonable means, this is the first time you have
    received notice of violation of this License (for any work) from that
    copyright holder, and you cure the violation prior to 30 days after your
    receipt of the notice.</para>

    <para>Termination of your rights under this section does not terminate the
    licenses of parties who have received copies or rights from you under this
    License. If your rights have been terminated and not permanently
    reinstated, you do not qualify to receive new licenses for the same
    material under section 10.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="AcceptanceNotRequired">9. Acceptance
    Not Required for Having Copies.</bridgehead>

    <para>You are not required to accept this License in order to receive or
    run a copy of the Program. Ancillary propagation of a covered work
    occurring solely as a consequence of using peer-to-peer transmission to
    receive a copy likewise does not require acceptance. However, nothing
    other than this License grants you permission to propagate or modify any
    covered work. These actions infringe copyright if you do not accept this
    License. Therefore, by modifying or propagating a covered work, you
    indicate your acceptance of this License to do so.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="AutomaticDownstream">10. Automatic
    Licensing of Downstream Recipients.</bridgehead>

    <para>Each time you convey a covered work, the recipient automatically
    receives a license from the original licensors, to run, modify and
    propagate that work, subject to this License. You are not responsible for
    enforcing compliance by third parties with this License.</para>

    <para>An “entity transaction” is a transaction transferring control of an
    organization, or substantially all assets of one, or subdividing an
    organization, or merging organizations. If propagation of a covered work
    results from an entity transaction, each party to that transaction who
    receives a copy of the work also receives whatever licenses to the work
    the party's predecessor in interest had or could give under the previous
    paragraph, plus a right to possession of the Corresponding Source of the
    work from the predecessor in interest, if the predecessor has it or can
    get it with reasonable efforts.</para>

    <para>You may not impose any further restrictions on the exercise of the
    rights granted or affirmed under this License. For example, you may not
    impose a license fee, royalty, or other charge for exercise of rights
    granted under this License, and you may not initiate litigation (including
    a cross-claim or counterclaim in a lawsuit) alleging that any patent claim
    is infringed by making, using, selling, offering for sale, or importing
    the Program or any portion of it.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="Patents">11. Patents.</bridgehead>

    <para>A “contributor” is a copyright holder who authorizes use under this
    License of the Program or a work on which the Program is based. The work
    thus licensed is called the contributor's “contributor version”.</para>

    <para>A contributor's “essential patent claims” are all patent claims
    owned or controlled by the contributor, whether already acquired or
    hereafter acquired, that would be infringed by some manner, permitted by
    this License, of making, using, or selling its contributor version, but do
    not include claims that would be infringed only as a consequence of
    further modification of the contributor version. For purposes of this
    definition, “control” includes the right to grant patent sublicenses in a
    manner consistent with the requirements of this License.</para>

    <para>Each contributor grants you a non-exclusive, worldwide, royalty-free
    patent license under the contributor's essential patent claims, to make,
    use, sell, offer for sale, import and otherwise run, modify and propagate
    the contents of its contributor version.</para>

    <para>In the following three paragraphs, a “patent license” is any express
    agreement or commitment, however denominated, not to enforce a patent
    (such as an express permission to practice a patent or covenant not to sue
    for patent infringement). To “grant” such a patent license to a party
    means to make such an agreement or commitment not to enforce a patent
    against the party.</para>

    <para>If you convey a covered work, knowingly relying on a patent license,
    and the Corresponding Source of the work is not available for anyone to
    copy, free of charge and under the terms of this License, through a
    publicly available network server or other readily accessible means, then
    you must either (1) cause the Corresponding Source to be so available, or
    (2) arrange to deprive yourself of the benefit of the patent license for
    this particular work, or (3) arrange, in a manner consistent with the
    requirements of this License, to extend the patent license to downstream
    recipients. “Knowingly relying” means you have actual knowledge that, but
    for the patent license, your conveying the covered work in a country, or
    your recipient's use of the covered work in a country, would infringe one
    or more identifiable patents in that country that you have reason to
    believe are valid.</para>

    <para>If, pursuant to or in connection with a single transaction or
    arrangement, you convey, or propagate by procuring conveyance of, a
    covered work, and grant a patent license to some of the parties receiving
    the covered work authorizing them to use, propagate, modify or convey a
    specific copy of the covered work, then the patent license you grant is
    automatically extended to all recipients of the covered work and works
    based on it.</para>

    <para>A patent license is “discriminatory” if it does not include within
    the scope of its coverage, prohibits the exercise of, or is conditioned on
    the non-exercise of one or more of the rights that are specifically
    granted under this License. You may not convey a covered work if you are a
    party to an arrangement with a third party that is in the business of
    distributing software, under which you make payment to the third party
    based on the extent of your activity of conveying the work, and under
    which the third party grants, to any of the parties who would receive the
    covered work from you, a discriminatory patent license (a) in connection
    with copies of the covered work conveyed by you (or copies made from those
    copies), or (b) primarily for and in connection with specific products or
    compilations that contain the covered work, unless you entered into that
    arrangement, or that patent license was granted, prior to 28 March
    2007.</para>

    <para>Nothing in this License shall be construed as excluding or limiting
    any implied license or other defenses to infringement that may otherwise
    be available to you under applicable patent law.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="NoSurrender">12. No Surrender of
    Others' Freedom.</bridgehead>

    <para>If conditions are imposed on you (whether by court order, agreement
    or otherwise) that contradict the conditions of this License, they do not
    excuse you from the conditions of this License. If you cannot convey a
    covered work so as to satisfy simultaneously your obligations under this
    License and any other pertinent obligations, then as a consequence you may
    not convey it at all. For example, if you agree to terms that obligate you
    to collect a royalty for further conveying from those to whom you convey
    the Program, the only way you could satisfy both those terms and this
    License would be to refrain entirely from conveying the Program.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="UsedWithAGPL">13. Use with the
    <acronym>GNU</acronym> Affero General Public License.</bridgehead>

    <para>Notwithstanding any other provision of this License, you have
    permission to link or combine any covered work with a work licensed under
    version 3 of the <acronym>GNU</acronym> Affero General Public License into
    a single combined work, and to convey the resulting work. The terms of
    this License will continue to apply to the part which is the covered work,
    but the special requirements of the <acronym>GNU</acronym> Affero General
    Public License, section 13, concerning interaction through a network will
    apply to the combination as such.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="RevisedVersions">14. Revised Versions
    of this License.</bridgehead>

    <para>The Free Software Foundation may publish revised and/or new versions
    of the <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License from time to time.
    Such new versions will be similar in spirit to the present version, but
    may differ in detail to address new problems or concerns.</para>

    <para>Each version is given a distinguishing version number. If the
    Program specifies that a certain numbered version of the
    <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License “or any later version”
    applies to it, you have the option of following the terms and conditions
    either of that numbered version or of any later version published by the
    Free Software Foundation. If the Program does not specify a version number
    of the <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License, you may choose any
    version ever published by the Free Software Foundation.</para>

    <para>If the Program specifies that a proxy can decide which future
    versions of the <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License can be used,
    that proxy's public statement of acceptance of a version permanently
    authorizes you to choose that version for the Program.</para>

    <para>Later license versions may give you additional or different
    permissions. However, no additional obligations are imposed on any author
    or copyright holder as a result of your choosing to follow a later
    version.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="WarrantyDisclaimer">15. Disclaimer of
    Warranty.</bridgehead>

    <para>THERE IS NO WARRANTY FOR THE PROGRAM, TO THE EXTENT PERMITTED BY
    APPLICABLE LAW. EXCEPT WHEN OTHERWISE STATED IN WRITING THE COPYRIGHT
    HOLDERS AND/OR OTHER PARTIES PROVIDE THE PROGRAM “AS IS” WITHOUT WARRANTY
    OF ANY KIND, EITHER EXPRESSED OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO,
    THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
    PURPOSE. THE ENTIRE RISK AS TO THE QUALITY AND PERFORMANCE OF THE PROGRAM
    IS WITH YOU. SHOULD THE PROGRAM PROVE DEFECTIVE, YOU ASSUME THE COST OF
    ALL NECESSARY SERVICING, REPAIR OR CORRECTION.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="LiabilityLimitation">16. Limitation
    of Liability.</bridgehead>

    <para>IN NO EVENT UNLESS REQUIRED BY APPLICABLE LAW OR AGREED TO IN
    WRITING WILL ANY COPYRIGHT HOLDER, OR ANY OTHER PARTY WHO MODIFIES AND/OR
    CONVEYS THE PROGRAM AS PERMITTED ABOVE, BE LIABLE TO YOU FOR DAMAGES,
    INCLUDING ANY GENERAL, SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
    ARISING OUT OF THE USE OR INABILITY TO USE THE PROGRAM (INCLUDING BUT NOT
    LIMITED TO LOSS OF DATA OR DATA BEING RENDERED INACCURATE OR LOSSES
    SUSTAINED BY YOU OR THIRD PARTIES OR A FAILURE OF THE PROGRAM TO OPERATE
    WITH ANY OTHER PROGRAMS), EVEN IF SUCH HOLDER OR OTHER PARTY HAS BEEN
    ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGES.</para>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="InterpretationSecs1516">17.
    Interpretation of Sections 15 and 16.</bridgehead>

    <para>If the disclaimer of warranty and limitation of liability provided
    above cannot be given local legal effect according to their terms,
    reviewing courts shall apply local law that most closely approximates an
    absolute waiver of all civil liability in connection with the Program,
    unless a warranty or assumption of liability accompanies a copy of the
    Program in return for a fee.</para>

    <bridgehead>END OF TERMS AND CONDITIONS</bridgehead>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect1" xml:id="HowToApply">How to Apply These Terms
    to Your New Programs</bridgehead>

    <para>If you develop a new program, and you want it to be of the greatest
    possible use to the public, the best way to achieve this is to make it
    free software which everyone can redistribute and change under these
    terms.</para>

    <para>To do so, attach the following notices to the program. It is safest
    to attach them to the start of each source file to most effectively state
    the exclusion of warranty; and each file should have at least the
    “copyright” line and a pointer to where the full notice is found.</para>

    <screen>
  <replaceable>one line to give the program's name and a brief idea of what it does.</replaceable>
  Copyright (C) <replaceable>year</replaceable> <replaceable>name of author</replaceable>
  
  This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
  it under the terms of the <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License as published by
  the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or
  (at your option) any later version.
  
  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
  <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License for more details.
  
  You should have received a copy of the <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License
  along with this program.  If not, see <link
        xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/">http://www.gnu.org/licenses/</link>.
    </screen>

    <para>Also add information on how to contact you by electronic and paper
    mail.</para>

    <para>If the program does terminal interaction, make it output a short
    notice like this when it starts in an interactive mode:</para>

    <screen>
  <replaceable>program</replaceable> Copyright (C) <replaceable>year</replaceable> <replaceable>name of author</replaceable>
  This program comes with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY; for details type '<literal>show w</literal>'.
  This is free software, and you are welcome to redistribute it
  under certain conditions; type '<literal>show c</literal>' for details.
    </screen>

    <para>The hypothetical commands '<literal>show w</literal>' and
    '<literal>show c</literal>' should show the appropriate parts of the
    General Public License. Of course, your program's commands might be
    different; for a GUI interface, you would use an “about box”.</para>

    <para>You should also get your employer (if you work as a programmer) or
    school, if any, to sign a “copyright disclaimer” for the program, if
    necessary. For more information on this, and how to apply and follow the
    <acronym>GNU</acronym> <acronym>GPL</acronym>, see <link
    xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/">http://www.gnu.org/licenses/</link>.</para>

    <para>The <acronym>GNU</acronym> General Public License does not permit
    incorporating your program into proprietary programs. If your program is a
    subroutine library, you may consider it more useful to permit linking
    proprietary applications with the library. If this is what you want to do,
    use the <acronym>GNU</acronym> Lesser General Public License instead of
    this License. But first, please read <link
    xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/why-not-lgpl.html">http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/why-not-lgpl.html</link>.</para>
  </appendix>

  <appendix xml:id="fdl">
    <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>

    <simpara>Version 1.3, 3 November 2008</simpara>

    <simpara>Copyright © 2000, 2001, 2002, 2007, 2008 <link
    xlink:href="http://www.fsf.org/">Free Software Foundation,
    Inc.</link></simpara>

    <simpara>Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies of
    this license document, but changing it is not allowed.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section0">0. PREAMBLE</bridgehead>

    <simpara>The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or
    other functional and useful document “free” in the sense of freedom: to
    assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it, with or
    without modifying it, either commercially or noncommercially. Secondarily,
    this License preserves for the author and publisher a way to get credit
    for their work, while not being considered responsible for modifications
    made by others.</simpara>

    <simpara>This License is a kind of “copyleft”, which means that derivative
    works of the document must themselves be free in the same sense. It
    complements the GNU General Public License, which is a copyleft license
    designed for free software.</simpara>

    <simpara>We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals for
    free software, because free software needs free documentation: a free
    program should come with manuals providing the same freedoms that the
    software does. But this License is not limited to software manuals; it can
    be used for any textual work, regardless of subject matter or whether it
    is published as a printed book. We recommend this License principally for
    works whose purpose is instruction or reference.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section1">1. APPLICABILITY AND
    DEFINITIONS</bridgehead>

    <simpara>This License applies to any manual or other work, in any medium,
    that contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be
    distributed under the terms of this License. Such a notice grants a
    world-wide, royalty-free license, unlimited in duration, to use that work
    under the conditions stated herein. The “Document”, below, refers to any
    such manual or work. Any member of the public is a licensee, and is
    addressed as “you”. You accept the license if you copy, modify or
    distribute the work in a way requiring permission under copyright
    law.</simpara>

    <simpara>A “Modified Version” of the Document means any work containing
    the Document or a portion of it, either copied verbatim, or with
    modifications and/or translated into another language.</simpara>

    <simpara>A “Secondary Section” is a named appendix or a front-matter
    section of the Document that deals exclusively with the relationship of
    the publishers or authors of the Document to the Document’s overall
    subject (or to related matters) and contains nothing that could fall
    directly within that overall subject. (Thus, if the Document is in part a
    textbook of mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any
    mathematics.) The relationship could be a matter of historical connection
    with the subject or with related matters, or of legal, commercial,
    philosophical, ethical or political position regarding them.</simpara>

    <simpara>The “Invariant Sections” are certain Secondary Sections whose
    titles are designated, as being those of Invariant Sections, in the notice
    that says that the Document is released under this License. If a section
    does not fit the above definition of Secondary then it is not allowed to
    be designated as Invariant. The Document may contain zero Invariant
    Sections. If the Document does not identify any Invariant Sections then
    there are none.</simpara>

    <simpara>The “Cover Texts” are certain short passages of text that are
    listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the notice that says
    that the Document is released under this License. A Front-Cover Text may
    be at most 5 words, and a Back-Cover Text may be at most 25
    words.</simpara>

    <simpara>A “Transparent” copy of the Document means a machine-readable
    copy, represented in a format whose specification is available to the
    general public, that is suitable for revising the document
    straightforwardly with generic text editors or (for images composed of
    pixels) generic paint programs or (for drawings) some widely available
    drawing editor, and that is suitable for input to text formatters or for
    automatic translation to a variety of formats suitable for input to text
    formatters. A copy made in an otherwise Transparent file format whose
    markup, or absence of markup, has been arranged to thwart or discourage
    subsequent modification by readers is not Transparent. An image format is
    not Transparent if used for any substantial amount of text. A copy that is
    not “Transparent” is called “Opaque”.</simpara>

    <simpara>Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include plain
    ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input format, SGML or
    XML using a publicly available DTD, and standard-conforming simple HTML,
    PostScript or PDF designed for human modification. Examples of transparent
    image formats include PNG, XCF and JPG. Opaque formats include proprietary
    formats that can be read and edited only by proprietary word processors,
    SGML or XML for which the DTD and/or processing tools are not generally
    available, and the machine-generated HTML, PostScript or PDF produced by
    some word processors for output purposes only.</simpara>

    <simpara>The “Title Page” means, for a printed book, the title page
    itself, plus such following pages as are needed to hold, legibly, the
    material this License requires to appear in the title page. For works in
    formats which do not have any title page as such, “Title Page” means the
    text near the most prominent appearance of the work’s title, preceding the
    beginning of the body of the text.</simpara>

    <simpara>The “publisher” means any person or entity that distributes
    copies of the Document to the public.</simpara>

    <simpara>A section “Entitled XYZ” means a named subunit of the Document
    whose title either is precisely XYZ or contains XYZ in parentheses
    following text that translates XYZ in another language. (Here XYZ stands
    for a specific section name mentioned below, such as “Acknowledgements”,
    “Dedications”, “Endorsements”, or “History”.) To “Preserve the Title” of
    such a section when you modify the Document means that it remains a
    section “Entitled XYZ” according to this definition.</simpara>

    <simpara>The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the notice
    which states that this License applies to the Document. These Warranty
    Disclaimers are considered to be included by reference in this License,
    but only as regards disclaiming warranties: any other implication that
    these Warranty Disclaimers may have is void and has no effect on the
    meaning of this License.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section2">2. VERBATIM
    COPYING</bridgehead>

    <simpara>You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium, either
    commercially or noncommercially, provided that this License, the copyright
    notices, and the license notice saying this License applies to the
    Document are reproduced in all copies, and that you add no other
    conditions whatsoever to those of this License. You may not use technical
    measures to obstruct or control the reading or further copying of the
    copies you make or distribute. However, you may accept compensation in
    exchange for copies. If you distribute a large enough number of copies you
    must also follow the conditions in section 3.</simpara>

    <simpara>You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated above,
    and you may publicly display copies.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section3">3. COPYING IN
    QUANTITY</bridgehead>

    <simpara>If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that commonly
    have printed covers) of the Document, numbering more than 100, and the
    Document’s license notice requires Cover Texts, you must enclose the
    copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly, all these Cover Texts:
    Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back
    cover. Both covers must also clearly and legibly identify you as the
    publisher of these copies. The front cover must present the full title
    with all words of the title equally prominent and visible. You may add
    other material on the covers in addition. Copying with changes limited to
    the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the Document and satisfy
    these conditions, can be treated as verbatim copying in other
    respects.</simpara>

    <simpara>If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit
    legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit reasonably)
    on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto adjacent pages.</simpara>

    <simpara>If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document
    numbering more than 100, you must either include a machine-readable
    Transparent copy along with each Opaque copy, or state in or with each
    Opaque copy a computer-network location from which the general
    network-using public has access to download using public-standard network
    protocols a complete Transparent copy of the Document, free of added
    material. If you use the latter option, you must take reasonably prudent
    steps, when you begin distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure
    that this Transparent copy will remain thus accessible at the stated
    location until at least one year after the last time you distribute an
    Opaque copy (directly or through your agents or retailers) of that edition
    to the public.</simpara>

    <simpara>It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors
    of the Document well before redistributing any large number of copies, to
    give them a chance to provide you with an updated version of the
    Document.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section4">4.
    MODIFICATIONS</bridgehead>

    <simpara>You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the Document
    under the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided that you release
    the Modified Version under precisely this License, with the Modified
    Version filling the role of the Document, thus licensing distribution and
    modification of the Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy of it. In
    addition, you must do these things in the Modified Version:</simpara>

    <orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
      <listitem>
        <simpara>Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a title
        distinct from that of the Document, and from those of previous
        versions (which should, if there were any, be listed in the History
        section of the Document). You may use the same title as a previous
        version if the original publisher of that version gives
        permission.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more persons or
        entities responsible for authorship of the modifications in the
        Modified Version, together with at least five of the principal authors
        of the Document (all of its principal authors, if it has fewer than
        five), unless they release you from this requirement.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>State on the Title page the name of the publisher of the
        Modified Version, as the publisher.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve all the copyright notices of the Document.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications
        adjacent to the other copyright notices.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a license
        notice giving the public permission to use the Modified Version under
        the terms of this License, in the form shown in the Addendum
        below.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve in that license notice the full lists of Invariant
        Sections and required Cover Texts given in the Document’s license
        notice.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Include an unaltered copy of this License.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve the section Entitled “History”, Preserve its Title,
        and add to it an item stating at least the title, year, new authors,
        and publisher of the Modified Version as given on the Title Page. If
        there is no section Entitled “History” in the Document, create one
        stating the title, year, authors, and publisher of the Document as
        given on its Title Page, then add an item describing the Modified
        Version as stated in the previous sentence.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve the network location, if any, given in the Document
        for public access to a Transparent copy of the Document, and likewise
        the network locations given in the Document for previous versions it
        was based on. These may be placed in the “History” section. You may
        omit a network location for a work that was published at least four
        years before the Document itself, or if the original publisher of the
        version it refers to gives permission.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>For any section Entitled “Acknowledgements” or “Dedications”,
        Preserve the Title of the section, and preserve in the section all the
        substance and tone of each of the contributor acknowledgements and/or
        dedications given therein.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the Document,
        unaltered in their text and in their titles. Section numbers or the
        equivalent are not considered part of the section titles.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Delete any section Entitled “Endorsements”. Such a section
        may not be included in the Modified Version.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Do not retitle any existing section to be Entitled
        “Endorsements” or to conflict in title with any Invariant
        Section.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <simpara>Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers.</simpara>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <simpara>If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or
    appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material
    copied from the Document, you may at your option designate some or all of
    these sections as invariant. To do this, add their titles to the list of
    Invariant Sections in the Modified Version’s license notice. These titles
    must be distinct from any other section titles.</simpara>

    <simpara>You may add a section Entitled “Endorsements”, provided it
    contains nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by various
    parties — for example, statements of peer review or that the text has been
    approved by an organization as the authoritative definition of a
    standard.</simpara>

    <simpara>You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover Text,
    and a passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the end of the
    list of Cover Texts in the Modified Version. Only one passage of
    Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be added by (or through
    arrangements made by) any one entity. If the Document already includes a
    cover text for the same cover, previously added by you or by arrangement
    made by the same entity you are acting on behalf of, you may not add
    another; but you may replace the old one, on explicit permission from the
    previous publisher that added the old one.</simpara>

    <simpara>The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this
    License give permission to use their names for publicity for or to assert
    or imply endorsement of any Modified Version.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section5">5. COMBINING
    DOCUMENTS</bridgehead>

    <simpara>You may combine the Document with other documents released under
    this License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for modified
    versions, provided that you include in the combination all of the
    Invariant Sections of all of the original documents, unmodified, and list
    them all as Invariant Sections of your combined work in its license
    notice, and that you preserve all their Warranty Disclaimers.</simpara>

    <simpara>The combined work need only contain one copy of this License, and
    multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a single copy.
    If there are multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but different
    contents, make the title of each such section unique by adding at the end
    of it, in parentheses, the name of the original author or publisher of
    that section if known, or else a unique number. Make the same adjustment
    to the section titles in the list of Invariant Sections in the license
    notice of the combined work.</simpara>

    <simpara>In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled
    “History” in the various original documents, forming one section Entitled
    “History”; likewise combine any sections Entitled “Acknowledgements”, and
    any sections Entitled “Dedications”. You must delete all sections Entitled
    “Endorsements”.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section6">6. COLLECTIONS OF
    DOCUMENTS</bridgehead>

    <simpara>You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other
    documents released under this License, and replace the individual copies
    of this License in the various documents with a single copy that is
    included in the collection, provided that you follow the rules of this
    License for verbatim copying of each of the documents in all other
    respects.</simpara>

    <simpara>You may extract a single document from such a collection, and
    distribute it individually under this License, provided you insert a copy
    of this License into the extracted document, and follow this License in
    all other respects regarding verbatim copying of that document.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section7">7. AGGREGATION WITH
    INDEPENDENT WORKS</bridgehead>

    <simpara>A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other
    separate and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a
    storage or distribution medium, is called an “aggregate” if the copyright
    resulting from the compilation is not used to limit the legal rights of
    the compilation’s users beyond what the individual works permit. When the
    Document is included in an aggregate, this License does not apply to the
    other works in the aggregate which are not themselves derivative works of
    the Document.</simpara>

    <simpara>If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to these
    copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than one half of the
    entire aggregate, the Document’s Cover Texts may be placed on covers that
    bracket the Document within the aggregate, or the electronic equivalent of
    covers if the Document is in electronic form. Otherwise they must appear
    on printed covers that bracket the whole aggregate.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section8">8. TRANSLATION</bridgehead>

    <simpara>Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
    distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section 4.
    Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires special permission
    from their copyright holders, but you may include translations of some or
    all Invariant Sections in addition to the original versions of these
    Invariant Sections. You may include a translation of this License, and all
    the license notices in the Document, and any Warranty Disclaimers,
    provided that you also include the original English version of this
    License and the original versions of those notices and disclaimers. In
    case of a disagreement between the translation and the original version of
    this License or a notice or disclaimer, the original version will
    prevail.</simpara>

    <simpara>If a section in the Document is Entitled “Acknowledgements”,
    “Dedications”, or “History”, the requirement (section 4) to Preserve its
    Title (section 1) will typically require changing the actual
    title.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section9">9. TERMINATION</bridgehead>

    <simpara>You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the Document
    except as expressly provided under this License. Any attempt otherwise to
    copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute it is void, and will automatically
    terminate your rights under this License.</simpara>

    <simpara>However, if you cease all violation of this License, then your
    license from a particular copyright holder is reinstated (a)
    provisionally, unless and until the copyright holder explicitly and
    finally terminates your license, and (b) permanently, if the copyright
    holder fails to notify you of the violation by some reasonable means prior
    to 60 days after the cessation.</simpara>

    <simpara>Moreover, your license from a particular copyright holder is
    reinstated permanently if the copyright holder notifies you of the
    violation by some reasonable means, this is the first time you have
    received notice of violation of this License (for any work) from that
    copyright holder, and you cure the violation prior to 30 days after your
    receipt of the notice.</simpara>

    <simpara>Termination of your rights under this section does not terminate
    the licenses of parties who have received copies or rights from you under
    this License. If your rights have been terminated and not permanently
    reinstated, receipt of a copy of some or all of the same material does not
    give you any rights to use it.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section10">10. FUTURE REVISIONS OF
    THIS LICENSE</bridgehead>

    <simpara>The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions of
    the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time. Such new versions
    will be similar in spirit to the present version, but may differ in detail
    to address new problems or concerns. See <link
    xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/">Copyleft</link>.</simpara>

    <simpara>Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version
    number. If the Document specifies that a particular numbered version of
    this License “or any later version” applies to it, you have the option of
    following the terms and conditions either of that specified version or of
    any later version that has been published (not as a draft) by the Free
    Software Foundation. If the Document does not specify a version number of
    this License, you may choose any version ever published (not as a draft)
    by the Free Software Foundation. If the Document specifies that a proxy
    can decide which future versions of this License can be used, that proxy’s
    public statement of acceptance of a version permanently authorizes you to
    choose that version for the Document.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="section11">11.
    RELICENSING</bridgehead>

    <simpara>“Massive Multiauthor Collaboration Site” (or “MMC Site”) means
    any World Wide Web server that publishes copyrightable works and also
    provides prominent facilities for anybody to edit those works. A public
    wiki that anybody can edit is an example of such a server. A “Massive
    Multiauthor Collaboration” (or “MMC”) contained in the site means any set
    of copyrightable works thus published on the MMC site.</simpara>

    <simpara>“CC-BY-SA” means the Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0
    license published by Creative Commons Corporation, a not-for-profit
    corporation with a principal place of business in San Francisco,
    California, as well as future copyleft versions of that license published
    by that same organization.</simpara>

    <simpara>“Incorporate” means to publish or republish a Document, in whole
    or in part, as part of another Document.</simpara>

    <simpara>An MMC is “eligible for relicensing” if it is licensed under this
    License, and if all works that were first published under this License
    somewhere other than this MMC, and subsequently incorporated in whole or
    in part into the MMC, (1) had no cover texts or invariant sections, and
    (2) were thus incorporated prior to November 1, 2008.</simpara>

    <simpara>The operator of an MMC Site may republish an MMC contained in the
    site under CC-BY-SA on the same site at any time before August 1, 2009,
    provided the MMC is eligible for relicensing.</simpara>

    <bridgehead renderas="sect2" xml:id="addendum">ADDENDUM: How to use this
    License for your documents</bridgehead>

    <simpara>To use this License in a document you have written, include a
    copy of the License in the document and put the following copyright and
    license notices just after the title page:</simpara>

    <screen>Copyright © YEAR YOUR NAME
  
  Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the
  terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or any later version
  published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no
  Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included in
  the section entitled “GNU Free Documentation License”.</screen>

    <simpara>If you have Invariant Sections, Front-Cover Texts and Back-Cover
    Texts, replace the “with… Texts.” line with this:</simpara>

    <screen>with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the Front-Cover Texts
  being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST.</screen>

    <simpara>If you have Invariant Sections without Cover Texts, or some other
    combination of the three, merge those two alternatives to suit the
    situation.</simpara>

    <simpara>If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code, we
    recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your choice of free
    software license, such as the GNU General Public License, to permit their
    use in free software.</simpara>
  </appendix>
</book>
